<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A viewe of some part of such publike wants &amp; disorders as are in the seruice of God, within her Maiesties countrie of VVales togither vvith an humble petition, vnto this high Court of Parliament for their speedy redresse. Wherein is shevved, not only the necessitie of reforming the state of religion among that people, but also the onely way, in regarde of substaunce, to bring that reformation to passe.</title>
            <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114394</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849619</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849619</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14778</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09300)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14778)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 516:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A viewe of some part of such publike wants &amp; disorders as are in the seruice of God, within her Maiesties countrie of VVales togither vvith an humble petition, vnto this high Court of Parliament for their speedy redresse. Wherein is shevved, not only the necessitie of reforming the state of religion among that people, but also the onely way, in regarde of substaunce, to bring that reformation to passe.</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 83, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegrave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Coventry :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Iohn Penri.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A supplication vnto the high Court of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Puritan authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wales --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14778:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14778:1"/>
            <p>A viewe of ſome part of ſuch <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like wants &amp; diſorders as are in the ſeruice</hi> of God, within her Maieſties countrie <hi>of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ales, togither vvith an humble</hi> PETITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON, vnto this high Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their ſpeedy redreſſe.</p>
            <p>¶ WHEREIN IS SHEVVED, not only the neceſsitie of reforming the ſtate of religion among that people, but alſo the onely way, in regarde of ſubſtaunce, to bring that reformation to paſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14778:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14778:2"/>
            <head>¶ To all thoſe that faythfully loue <hi>the lord Ieſus, and vnfainedly deſire the</hi> flowriſhing eſtate of Sion, together <hi>vvith the vtter razing of vvhatſoeuer obſcureth the</hi> perfect beutie therof: &amp; namely, to ſuch of my brethren and countrimen, as the Lord hath enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a true knowledge, the ioy of an vpright and comfortable profeſſion, with the encreaſe of all other the Lords good graces, be multiplyed in Ieſus Chriſte our LORD.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I Am not ignoraunt (beloued in the</hi> Lord) hovv many and great cauſes there are, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the very leaſt might ſeeme to haue bene ſufficiently able to diſcourage me from this enterpriſe, vvhich vnder the holy hand of my God I haue novv vndertaken. J am guiltie vnto my ſelfe of great corruption and vveakenes. The glory of God is not ſo regarded amongeſt men as it ought to be. The Parliament hath hytherto reiected this cauſe: The enemies thereof are many and ſtrong. But as the diſcouragements are not a fevve, ſo J confeſſe my ſelf to be dravvn back vvith none more, then vvith the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of my ſelfe. For looking into mine ovvn hart, I do from the bottom therof protest, ſo ſinful, baſe, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible, and euery vvay ſo vveak a vvretch as J am, to be the vnfittest instrument vnder heauen, to deale in ſo vvaighty a cauſe. Jt commeth into my minde, that the Lord in iust iudgments tovvards my ſinnes, should deny any bleſſing vnto my endeuors. J knovv that my vveak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in handling the cauſe, might diſgrace the ſame. And inaſmuch as ſtates for the most part, looke vvith fleshly eyes; It commeth into my minde, that the ſuit, by reaſon of my baſe eſtate should be reiected and cast off. But all thoſe likelihoods notvvithstanding: yet I ſee that the <pb facs="tcp:14778:3"/> Lord vvill haue the cauſe once againe brought vnto the Parliament in my hands, to try vvhether men vvill not acknovvledge the Gopell, and the gouernment of his ſon; to vvit, the ſcepter, vvhereby alone Christ Ieſus ruleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, to be vvorth the entertaynment in their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, thogh it be not accompanied vvith that vvorld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maiesty, vvhervvith vvhen it pleaſeth him, he is able to countenance it. And hereby it is in deed, that men do truly sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vv themſelues to tremble before the ſon of God, and to ſtoop vnto his royall Scepter, vvhen they are not ashamed of his vvord, hovv baſe ſoeuer they be that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuiters in the behalfe therof.</p>
            <p>For mine ovvne part, hovvſoeuer I haue iust occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to lament mine ovvne great corruptions, yet J may boldly ſay in the preſence of God, &amp; al thoſe, vnto vvhoſe conſideration theſe labors of mine are offred, publish thus much, that this cauſe, as near as I could, is altogither ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from thoſe foul ſtaines, vvhervvith J acknovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my ſelfe to be defiled. And J hope, that it ſo offereth it ſelfe vnto the publike vievv and conſideration of the Parliament, as they haue no iust cauſe by reaſon of my great vveaknes and baſe estate, to reiect the ſame. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is any man to maruell, that J being charged of late, by M. Doct. <hi>Some</hi> in publike vvriting, to be not onely a defender of many blasphemous errors, but alſo an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner of the ciuill State, durst preſume to become a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor vnto the high Court of Parliament, before J had firſt cleared my ſelfe of thoſe crimes. For my purpoſe being to haue published an anſvvere to M.D. <hi>Some,</hi> before this cauſe should be made knovvn; I vvas dravvne vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I vvould or no, to take the opportunity of ſetting out this, vvhich I thought to be most vvaighty; leaſt that if I had deferred it vntill th'other had come forth, I might <pb facs="tcp:14778:3"/> haue bin preuented of the means to publish it in any due time. Beſides the
<hi>185.</hi> page, line <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>30.</hi> of M.D. <hi>Somes</hi> booke, vvherein he hath freely graunted me the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie betvveene vs; vvhich is, that vnpreaching miniſters, are no ministers, and conſequently, not to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated vvith: do euidently shevv, that he did not vvell knovv himſelfe vvhat he did in charging me, ſo far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond christian modesty, for defending nothing els in theſe points, but that vvhich his ovvne vvritings do publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vvitnes against him to be Gods truth. So that of al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other cauſes, his bare (and by his ovvne vvitnes, for the most part falſe) accuſations, ought least of all to diſvvade me from this labour, though I neuer ment to aunſvvere him. But by the grace of God he shalbe anſvvered, and that very shortly.</p>
            <p>And the Petition being in the behalfe of Gods honor, and the good of his Church, the ſmall regard that the Parliament hath had heretofore vnto ſuch ſuites, ought not greatly to diſcourage me, the nomber, might, povver, and authoritie of the enemies of the cauſe, much leſſe. He that ruleth the harts of men, can encline them to the ſetting forth of his ovvne glory vvhen he thinketh good. That vvhich the Lord, for ſome cauſe ſeeming good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his vviſdome, doth not grant at one time, he (being for the promoting of his honor) lightly bringeth to paſſe at ſome other ſeaſon. And the attempts of his children for the buylding of his Church, haue not alvvayes that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe vvhich they vvish vnder their hands. For he vſeth the endeuors of ſome, not to finish the building, but to be a preparation vnto that vvorke which he meaneth to effect by the hand of others.
<hi>Zerubabel</hi> and <hi>Ezra</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored very hardly in the building of Ieruſalem; the Lord did not finish the vvorke by their means: and yet that
<pb facs="tcp:14778:4"/> vvhich they did, vvas a great furtherance vnto <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> vvhoſe hands the Lord vſed in ioyning the vvall. So the endeuors of Gods children in our dayes, may haue their effect to the glory of God, and the comfort of his Church amongst our posterities.</p>
            <p>It vvas a common demaund the laſt Parliament, vvhere the cauſe of reformation (being then labored for) vvas <hi>26.</hi> or <hi>28.</hi> years agone, and vvherfore after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years of the Gospell, enioyed in this land, the motion of altering the outvvard ſtate of the Church, in the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and officers therof? Came it ſo out of time to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered off? Leaſt the like obiection should be vſed in the ages to come; behold, the mountayns of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ales, do novv in the <hi>31.</hi> yeare of the raign of Queen <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> call heauen and earth to vvitnes, that they are vveary of their dumb miniſters, nonreſidents, Lord Bishops, &amp;c. and that they deſire to be vvatered by the devve of Chriſts holy Gospell, and to be compaſſed about, vvith that beautifull vvall of his holy gouernment. Be it then granted, that the Lord in anger tovvards our ſins, doth not account vs novv liuing, vvorthy to be inuited by hir right excellent Maiesty and the ſtate, as Jſrael vvas ſomtimes, by the godly king
<hi>Hezekiah;</hi> to giue the hand to the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Chro.
31.8</note> and to come vnto the Sanctuary vvhich he hath choſen, &amp; ſerue the Lord our God, that the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his vvrath should turne avvay from vs: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding, leaſt it should be preiudiciall vnto our children, that vve neuer claymed any intereſt vnto the trueth of the Gospell, and neuer deſired to be vnburde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of our blinde and tyrannicall guydes: This Petition of mine shalbe a vvitnes that both hath bin labored for. VVhoſoeuer they be then, that vvould vvish men, not to trouble themſelues in that cauſe, vvherein in their <pb facs="tcp:14778:4"/> iudgements, they can ſee no hope of preuayling; doe not conſider, that thereby they bereaue our poſterities of a great means, to come by that vvhich the children of God novv liuing, vvould ſo vvillingly obtaine. And they do not conſider, that as the Lord hath appointed ſome to lay the foundation, &amp; make vp the buylding of his Church; ſo he hath ordayned others, to prepare, and as it vvere, to clenſe the place vvhere he meaneth to buyld his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>The aduerſaries of this cauſe may be many, and of great countenance; but vve knovve that the Lord hath committed all povver in heauen, and in earth, not vnto man, but vnto his ovvne ſonne Chriſte Jeſus, the alone head and king ouer his Church.<note place="margin">Math. 28.18</note> The cauſe therefore in hand being his, in vvhoſe hands is all povver and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; vvhy should vve feare any thing that earth can inuent againſt the ſame? And if the question vvere, vvho ought to be terrified in this matter, they by vvhom the Petition is promoted, or they vvho oppugne the ſame: it shall be found that the aduerſaries hereof, haue no other cauſe, but to be ſtroken vvith a desperate and vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable feare: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hereas on the other ſide, the patrons of the ſuite may be euery vvay exceedingly comforted. For vvhat els do the enemies hereof, <hi>but</hi> (after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the vvicked mencioned in the booke of <hi>IOB) ſay vnto the Almighty, depart thou from vs?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13 15.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes,</hi> any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then it may ſtand vvith the vpholding of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions receaued and mayntained in our Church, by the conſent of the State. Yea, and in their practize they ſay, vvho is the Almighty that vve should ſerue him; if he be ſo ſtrickt in his vvorshipp, that he cannot abide a Church gouernment to be mayntained, vvhich may be
<pb facs="tcp:14778:5"/> changeable, at the pleaſure of the ciuill State? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ho is the Almighty that vve should ſerue him; if none muſt he in our miniſtery, but ſuch as both for their gifts and faythfulnes, do in deed shevv themſelues to be his true meſſengers? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ho is the Almighty that vve should ſerue him; if men for the bettering of their outvvard ſtate, may not be Lords ouer their brethren, and ioyn li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vvith liuing, that they may be able to maynayne a part vnbeſeeming their calling. And I vvould they did not ſay, vvhat profit is there, if vve did ſtoup ſo lovv vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as vvithout delay, there should nothing be in our Church, vvhich might ſvvarue from that ſeuere rule of his vvord? Should Gods children then feare leaſt theſe men should haue the vpper hand ouer them, and the Lords cauſe vvhich they mayntayn. Nay, I tell you, that although ſuch aduerſaries, vvere of that povver and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that it might be demaunded, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ho they vvere that durſt preſume to declare their euill vvayes vnto their faces: yet should they vndoutedly be made as ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before the vvind, and as the chaff, vvhich the ſtorm caryeth avvay. For this cauſe and euery one, that in the ſincerity of his hart, ſeeketh the prosperous ſucceſſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, may boldly ſay vvith <hi>IOB: Mine enemie ſhalbe as the wicked;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob.
27.7. &amp; 20.27. &amp; 21.10.</note> 
               <hi>and he that riſeth againſt me, as the vnrighteous, the heauens ſhall declare his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and the earth ſhall riſe vp againſt him. The encreaſe of his houſe ſhall go away, it ſhall flowe away in the day of his wrath, his eyes ſhall ſee his deſtruction, and he ſhall drinke of the wrath of the Almightie.</hi> This shalbe the portion of as many as to the end, oppoſe themſelues againſt the cauſe of reformation novv labored for. Jt is not a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of dalliance, to vvithſtand the povverfull ordinance <pb facs="tcp:14778:5"/> of God, in the gouerment of his Church, especially vvhen in the ſteede thereof, the marchandize of shameleſſe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon is maintayned. Jt is but folly to fight againſt the lambe, in the defence of her pleaſant things; For the lamb shall ouercome, becauſe he is the king of kings, and the Lord of Lords, and they that are of his ſide, choſen, and called, and faythfull. Great Babylon the mother, that mighty harlot, being in her ful ſtrength in this land, vvas not able to ſtand against him; vvhat then shall it boote the vveake daughter to ſtriue? And let them feare and take heede, vvho defend the daughters fornication, leaſt they be made partakers of the punishment denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, vvho committed adultery vvith the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Themſelues they may hurt, but their practizes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Gods trueth and his Sayntes, ought not to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Lords choſen, from ſtanding to the cauſe of their master. Be they then neuer ſo many, neuer ſo povverfull, neuer ſo flovvrishing, neuer of ſo great authority in the eyes of the vvorld, vvho cannot abide that the Gospell should haue ſuch a free paſſage in this kingdome, as the heat thereof shoulde melt vvhatſoeuer is amiſſe in our ſtate; yet the Lorde not being of their ſide in this poynt, they shall not be able to preuaile. For this is that cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vvhich, neuer man as yet ſtriued and prospered. J knovve there vvill be many in this Parliament, vvho questionleſſe fauor the cauſe of God from their heart, &amp; vvould be forvvard in pleading for the ſoueraigntie of Christ Ieſus, if they ſavv not their endeuors croſſed and vvithstood, by many of high place and authoritye. All thoſe vvhoſoeuer they be, J do from the bottome of mine heart earnestly beſeech, that they vvould conſider, that in dealing for the putting dovvne of the dumbe ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for the abolishing of Nonreſidency, and the rooting out of Lord Archb. and Lord Bishops, and vvhatſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:14778:6"/> els the right hand of the Lord hath not planted: and in ſeeing that the vvorde preached, may freely ſound tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout this kingdome, they do therby nothing els, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the God of heauen and earth may be acknoled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and accounted vvorthy alone to rule in his Church vvithin this land. The conſideration vvhereof, ought ſo to mooue and ſtir them vp, as no creature vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen should be able to diſmay them, in this their Petition and request. They ſeeke that he may rule his Church by his vvord and lavves alone, at vvhoſe reproffe the<note n="a" place="margin">2 Iob.
21.12</note> pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of heauen do tremble and quake. They ſeeke that he may be acknovvledged for the onely Sauiour and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of men, and for the onely lavvgiuer in his Church, vvho hath protested that he vvil not abide to impart the glory thereof vnto any other. And vvhom should they then feare in this ſuite? The Lorde hath promiſed, that none vvho trust in him shall perish, Pſal. <hi>34.22.</hi> And he hath promiſed, that although the vvicked vvatch to ſlay the righteous, yet he vvill not leaue him in his hand, pſal.
<hi>37.32.</hi> Yea, he hath promiſed to be vvith thoſe that fear him, vvhen they<note place="margin">Eſay. 48.1.2.</note> paſſe through the vvaters, that they should not be ouerflovven; and vvhen they vvalke tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the fire, that they should not be burnt. VVherefore then, shold they fear man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrels, as long as they ſincerely ſtand to the cauſe of their God. Though they be but a fevv in nomber, yet the Lord vvith legions of Angels ſtandeth on their ſide, to d ſcomfite all thoſe that contende vvith him. Oh J vvould that the vvords of the Lord ſpoken by
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet, vvere thoroughly vvritten in the hearts of as many in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable aſſembly, as for the feare of man vvill be the hardliar dravvn, throughly to ſtand to the cauſe of their God. For thus comfortably the Prophet, Chap. <hi>51</hi> of his propheſie, ſpeaketh vnto all thoſe that vvith an vpright <pb facs="tcp:14778:6"/> heart ſeeke the honor of the Lord. <hi>Heare me, ye that follow after righteouſnes, and ye that ſeeke the Lord, looke to the rocke whence you are hewen, and to the hole of the pitt whence you are dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. Conſider Abraham your father, and Sarah that bare you; for I called him alone and bleſſed him, and encreaſed him. Hearken vnto me, yee that know righteouſnes, and the people in whoſe hearts is my law, fear ye not the reproch of men, neither be you afraide of their rebukes: I, euen I am he that comfort you. Who art thou that thou ſhouldeſt feare a mortall man, and the ſonne of man, which ſhalbe made as graſſe, and forgetteſt the Lorde thy maker, which hath ſpredd out the heuens, &amp; layd the foundations of the earth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Novv then, vvhoſoeuer they be, that are timerous in the cauſe of God, (as alaſſe, vvhat flesh and blood is not too too feareful) here is a ſtedfaſt rocke for them to leane vnto; here is a defender for them, vnder the shadovv of vvhoſe vvings, they might be bold to contemne vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer their aduerſaries can bring against them. Are they but a fevv in nomber, let them looke vnto Abraham, he vvas called alone, and yet the Lord bleſſed him, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed him. Are they afrayd of the rebukes of man? vvhy they ſeeke the righteous vvayes of the Lord, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he commandeth them not to feare. Are they povv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull and mighty, by vvhom the ſuit is d ſcountenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: yea, but notvvithſtanding they are but mortall, &amp; they shalbe made as graſſe, and the time vvill come, vvherein it shalbe demanded; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>here are they novv that vvithſtood the cauſe of God in the Parliament of England? Js not their memory vvritten in vvater, and their hope perished together vvith them? To deſire the free paſſage of the Gospell in this land, together vvith <pb facs="tcp:14778:7"/> the ſpeedie remoouing of all that hindereth the ſame, is to plead the cauſe of that God, vvho hath controlled kings and great Monarches, yea quite ouerthrovvne them &amp; their kingdomes, for denying the free vſe of his ſeruice vvithin their dominions. Euen the cauſe of that God, vvho hath not onely brideled the rage of tyrants, enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſuppreſſion of his trueth, but alſo turned that, vnto the great good of his Church, vvhereby they ſought to vvorke the ruine thereof. Pharaoh, Achitophel, Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib, Haman, came to the graue vvith blood, vvhen in the eyes of men, the most of them vvere likeliest to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, and the cauſe of God and his children vnlikeliest to ſtand. The Lord in this kingdom can do the like vvhen he thinketh good.<note place="margin">Ezra.
4.7.8. &amp; 5.3. Cap. 6.7. &amp; 7.23.</note> The accuſations and ſlanders of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridath, Tabeel, Rehum, Shimſai, Shetherboznai, vvith their companions, did ſeeme likely once and againe, to hinder the buylding of the holy citie: but at the length it broght fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Darius, a most ſure &amp; ſtrong commandement for the furtherance of the work, clean contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the enemie. And vvho knovveth vvhether the Lord at this Parliament, vvill not ſtir vp the ſpirits of the Sates, and especially, of her R. excellent Maiestie, that they may ſay vnto the enemies of this cauſe, as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius did vnto the men aforenamed. Therefore Tatnai, captaine beyond the riuer, &amp; Shetherboznai vvith their companions; be ye far from them. Suffer the vvorke of this houſe of God to go forvvard. And<note n="a" place="margin">Ezra. 7.23.</note> vvhatſoeuer is by the commandement of the God of heauen, let it be done ſpeedely for the houſe of the God of heauen; for vvhy should he be vvroth against the realm, &amp;c. vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beloued, vvhoſoeuer you be, that at any time shalbe imployed, eyther as Parliament or othervviſe, in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forvvard of the cauſe of reformation, ſtand man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in defence of the truth, &amp; the liberty of his Church</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14778:7"/>The practiſes of the aduerſaries, I mean of our bishops, shevv manifeſtly, that theſe reliques of curſed Babylon, vvhich they maintayne among vs, must needs go avvay vvith a noyſe, as the rest vvas ouerthrovvne. They vvill not yeelde to the trueth, hovvſoeuer it hath gotten the vpper hande of them. The Lord must vſe violence to throvv them out, as he did against the caterpillers their forefathers. Reuel. <hi>18.19.</hi> They haue manifeſted hitherto, hovv desperate and paſt recouery, the cauſe vvhich they defend is become, in that they haue denyed, to yeelde a quiet and a brotherly conference or disputation, vvith thoſe vvho are contrary minded vnto them. Jf J may but procure this vvith our BB. in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ales, I vvill looſe my life, if they be not ouerthrovven: vvhich I ſpeake not, vvithout the humble acknovvledgement of myne ovvne vveaknes. And let me not be thought by any, to deale too confidently, for J deale in a ſure and a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent cauſe, vvhich is not timerouſly to be delt in, but in the feare of God, vvith all boldnes to be ſtood to, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouched. And whenſoeuer they or any of theirs, shal but aduenture their places againſt my life; they shall perceiue by the grace of God, that there is ſtrength in the cauſe, which hitherto they haue withſtood to their ſmal gaine.</p>
            <p>Yea, but I might haue dealt more ſparingly againſt them. It vvere pity in deed, but J should intreat the high court of Parliament to heale the diſeaſe of my countrie, but ſo notvvithſtanding, as they vvould ſuffer the cauſe of the griefe and miſery thereof ſtill to remaine. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament should be ſued vnto for helpe, againſt the diſeaſe and bane of the country of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ales, but ſo as they vvould fauor the cauſes thereof. And vvhat malladie is there J pray you in our Church, vvhereof the dumbe miniſters, nonreſidents, our Lord BB. vvith the reſt of that vngodly generation are not the cauſe. J should ſpare them vvho ſpare not the Church, and in vvhoſe eyes the glory of God <pb facs="tcp:14778:8"/> is not eſteemed, and yet the Lord knovveth, I hate them no farther then they are Gods enemies. Their fauor I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not, as long as they continue to be the aduerſaries of the Church. If they vvould yeeld peace vnto it, I vvould be ſoon brought to lay dovvn my complaints againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Concerning you my deare countrimen, vvhom God of his infinit goodnes and mercy, hath tranſlated out of the kingdome of darknes, vnto the bleſſed poſſeſsion of the heauenly Ieruſalem; I beſeech you very earnestly, that you vvould be carefull to walk vvorthy the Gospel of chriſt. Be carefull hereof, vvhether your abode be in England or in VVales, and at any hand, endeuor to liue vvhere you may enioy the meanes of the vvord. And be carefull to haue the Lord purely vvorshipped in your families. Take heed of the profanenes, vvhereby the moſt novve liuing, are dravvn to contemne Gods iudgements againſt their ſinnes. The time vvil come, wherin it shalbe made known that your hope vvas not in vaine. Labor diligently, as far as your callings vvill ſuffer you, to be a means to conuay that treaſure vnto your country, vvhereof you your ſelues haue bin made partakers. Particularly, let me here put you in minde, R. honourable and vvorshipfull, vvho of my countrye are in this Parliament, to acquaint this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable court, vvith the miſeries of our country, and to be earneſt for a redreſſe. And you my brethren, vvho ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fit gifts, and are employed in the miniſtery, either in your ovvn countrie or in England, forget not I pray you, to be remembrancers of Sion, giue the Lord no reſt, vntill the righteouſnes thereof breake foorth as the light, and the ſaluation thereof as a burning lampe. J vvould to God that I might ioyne vvith you, and you vvith me, in ſome endeuor, vvhereby the means of ſaluation might be had in our natiue countrie; it is my harty deſire. The God of peace, who hath called vs to his eternall glory by Chriſt Ieſus, make vs perfect, confirme, ſtrengthen and ſtablish vs to the ende, Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14778:8"/>
            <head>A viewe of ſome part of ſuch <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like wants &amp; diſorders as are in the ſeruice</hi> of God, within her Maieſties countrie <hi>of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ales, togither vvith an humble</hi> PETITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON, vnto this high Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their ſpeedy redreſſe. <hi>Anno</hi>
1588.</head>
            <p>THe aeternall God, before whom I nowe ſtand, and ſhall ſtande in that day, eyther to be acquited or condemned; knoweth that the pitifull &amp; miſerable eſtate of my pitifull and miſerable countreimen, the inhabitants of Wales; doe inforce me in moſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and humble maner, at this time, both to lay open before your eyes, whoe by the prouidence of God, are now to be aſſembled togither in this highe court of parlament: the wantes and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the ſeruice of god in wales, my deere &amp; natiue country, and alſo to intreat with the like ſubmiſſion, that the ſame by your wiſdomes may be ſpeedely redreſſed. The Lords holy ſeruice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge that people hath many corruptions and more wants. Their caſe in regarde therof is very pitifull. Few or none there be who are thorowly touched to haue compaſſion thereof. The means of redreſſe is in the hands of this aſſembly, who are met together, to the end that al the ſubiects of this kingdome, may with fredome and liberty acquaint them with their ſuits and Petitions, for the promotinge of Gods glory, and the good of their cuntry. And therfore, in that I make known vnto this high court, the greefes of my country, &amp; deſire the redreſſe thereof; therin I neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14778:9"/> any thing which lieth not in your power to grant, nor craue that, wherin the caſe being neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by others, I may not lawfully be a ſuter. The reaſon that mooueth me thereunto, is the diſcharge of my duty towards the Lord my God, towards his Church, towatdes my natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and towards you of this honorable aſſemblie, which coulde not ſtand with my ſilence nowe in this ſuit. Concerning the Lorde, becauſe I am a pore wretched ſinner, vpon whom he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great mercies, in pardoning my great offences often committed againſt his maieſtie; I haue by his grace taken a bonde of my ſelfe, to ſeeke the promoting of his honor by al means poſſible: and in the ſeeking thereof, to vtter the truth as far as my calling wil permit, without reſpect of perſon, time, place, eſtate, or conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life whatſoeuer; and ſo to become an vtter enemie vnto all theſe corruptions (by what authoritie or perſon ſoeuer they be maintained) whereby his holy ſeruice is hindred. And therfore you of this honorable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly are not to maruel, that I both ſeeke the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of theſe corruptions in Wales, whereof a non I wil ſpeak more at larg, wherby the Lords holy and ſacred miniſtery is ſhamefully polluted, and his ſeruice with the ſaluation of his people greatly withſtood: and alſo lay vppon you whoſe authority, good name, credit, eſtimation, and high place, I ought and by the grace of god wil defend, againſt al the detractors therof, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the loſſe of my life when it ſhalbe needful; the ſtaine and diſcredit of denying gods heauenly truth, the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage joyned with the continuance of the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table miſerie of ſoules, and the defence of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14778:9"/> impietie, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gods own houſe, vnles you yeeld vnto the ſuit, whervnto at this preſent you are entreated to be fauorable. As for the Church of God into which I haue bin begotten thorowe the word preched, by means of my abode in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, in theſe peaceable dayes of her highnes. I haue wholly dedicated my ſelfe to ſeeke the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing eſtate thereof by labouring to beutifie the ſame, both in the plucking vp by the rootes, of theſe filthie Italian weedes, wherwith it is nowe miſerably deformed; and planting therein what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer might be for the comlines of Gods orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, in reſpect of my poore countrey; becauſe it pleaſed the Lord of life that therin I firſt ſawe the light of the ſunne, and haue been by my parents there liuing, brought vp in both the vniuerſities of this land, to the end if euer the Lord enabled me, I ſhould procure the good of my natiue country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. I haue vowed my ſelfe dutifully to benefite them al the waies I may. And in doing them good, I purpoſe not to reſpect mine own quietnes, yea or life, where my death can win them the goſpel. And wherein ſhal I ſtand my deare cuntrimen in any ſteed, if not by ſpeaking in their behalf then, when their wantes are moſt pitiful, &amp; they not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or not willing, to make knowne their miſerie? if not in bleſſing their deaf ears, in remouing the ſtumblinge blocke from before the eies of the blinde? if not in labouringe to bring them to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, who of their owne natures ſhould liue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in a worſe place to their woe? Their miſery at this day conſiſting partly, in the great igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God wherein they liue, partly in thoſe corruptions and vnlawful callings, where by the <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14778:10"/> Church generally within her maieſties domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is peſtered; I am nowe with all humilytie to ſeeke the redreſſe both of the one and the other at the handes of this honorable aſſembly. This ignoraunce alſo, and theſe corruptions ſtanding as enemies in the way to hinder my bretheren from eternal life, I profeſſe my ſelfe to ſeeke their overthrowe and confuſion, and by the Lords aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance as longe as I liue, neuer leaue either of both, vntill the Church of God in Wales be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened of ſuche vnnaturall plantes. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning you of this honorable aſſemblye, ſeing I haue receaued the former bleſſings throughe your handes by meanes of the outward peace, whereof hir right excellent maieſtie hath made the whole land partaker from the Lord, I cannot of conſcience; but in moſt humble ſubmiſſion &amp; reuerent manner, put you in minde of the eſtate wherein you ſtand before the Lord, vnleſſe at this your meetinge, there be order taken, for the reforming in Wales of ſuch things as now ſhalbe made known vnto you to be amiſſe, and you ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly with all reauerence and dutie, entreated to reforme. May it pleaſe you therefore to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that there is not only ſuch a defect of the ſeruice of the euerliuing God in all the publike meetinges for the moſt part, of all the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantes of Wales, hir maieſties free borne ſubiects and people: as the moſt pariſhes within that cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, want the means of ſaluation, and haue wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame all this time of her proſperous go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment: but alſo that there is ſuch corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in that part of Gods ſeruice which is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, as the Lords holy and ſacted miniſterie, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14778:10"/> with al other eccleſiaſtical functions, pertayning vnto the outwatd ſeruice of God, and the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Church, are moſt intollerablie abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and prophaned by ſuch as are there tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to intermedle with them. And may it pleaſe you in like ſort, that ſome order may be taken, whereby the ſeruice of God in his pure worſhip, being as you heare, many waies defectiue and corrupt among the people, may be without delay reſtored vnto the integritie, which ſhalbe accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the ſight of God, and the meanes of their ſaluation who profeſſe the ſame. This moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and moſt waightie petition, I am the rather encoraged at this time to prefer, in as much as it doth not only tend to the ſaluation of many thouſandes ſoules, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now (alaſſe) periſh in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable darknes and ignorance, but concerneth the furtherance, which is the point eſpecially to be reſpected, of the pure and ſincere worſhip of the eternall God. And it is that cauſe, being my ſecond incouragement, which you of this high court of parliament profeſſe all of you to fauour. For who is he that will not profeſſe him ſelf to be the fauorer of a ſuit tending to the honor of God, and the deliuerance of men from eternall woe and perdition? And it is that cauſe wherein e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of you are bound vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your alegeance vnto the Lord and her maieſty, laying al other maters aſide, firſt and principally to deale; and ſo to deale as you ſuffer not your ſelues, for any worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes, either by the vtter reiecting, or by the cold and careleſſe intertaining hereof, to betraie God, to betray his truth, to betraie the ſaluation of men, and to betray the whole kingdome vnto <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14778:11"/> the fiery wrath of Gods heauie diſpleaſure: Of all which ſinnes the Lord himſelfe findeth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth euery one of you to be guiltie, that will not labour at this time of your aſſemblie, for the promoting of the cauſe nowe in hand. And howeſoeuer in former times, he hath ſeemed hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto to wincke at the careleſſe reſpect, which you haue had to his true ſeruice: yet you are now to vnderſtand, that it is to be feared, leſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſpeedie deſtruction wil betide the whole kingdome, if the ſuite wherevppon the worſhipp of Gods owne Maieſtie ſtandeth; be as ſlenderly entreated of the parliament of England, as alway heretofore it hath bene. And that the petition may apear to be no other, then that, which he by whome alone all kingdoms and common welths are maintained, requireth without contradiction to be graunted, by this honourable aſſemblie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his heauie wrath and diſpleaſure, would be procured vpon the whole land. And that it may apear to be no other then that, the graunt where of, is the onlie way to ſaue them on whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half it is made; no other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which no ſtate, no kingdom, no councell, prince, potentate, high or lowe can denie, except they would ſhewe them ſelues to haue no care of religion and pietie: that theſe thinges I ſay may appear, we are to conſider more at large of the petition, and then whether it be ſuch, as vpon the denial thereof, the wrath and anger of God is to be expected, for to fal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, who ſhall denie the ſame, and the whol land for their ſinne. Nowe therefore, if there be nothing elſe required at your hand, in this whole treatiſe following, but that which the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14778:11"/> from heauen, pronounceth to be ſo neerly joined with the former points; as vpon the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of the ſuite, you ſhal openly declare, that you are an aſſembly wherein the Lords cauſe ſhal not be hard; an aſſemblie wherein the felicitie of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable men ſhall not be reſpected; an aſſembly who wittingly and willingly call for the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God vpon the whole kingdome; an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly wherein trueth, religion, and pietie can beare no ſwaye: then I hope that none will be found in this honorable court, to be ſuch an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie vnto the honor of God, the felicitie of men, and the quiet ſtate of this common wealth: none ſo prophane, wicked, and irreligious, as euen to thinke that the conſultation of this matter may be differred. But if on the other ſide, the ſuite be founde to be of no ſuch importance, as before is expreſſed, or if I be found to write any thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent vnto the former points, or not to haue behaued my ſelfe ſo dutifull in my ſtile and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of writing towards this honorable court, as it became the baſeſt vaſſel vnder heauen, hauing a calling to deale in the like cauſe, to carie himſelf towardes the princes of his people, then let not my life be precious in your ſight. Here therefore, with all humility and reuerence, before the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God, his elect Angels and Church, her right excellent, our dread ſoueraigne, Queene ELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZABETH; I call euerye one of you to recorde, that vpon the perill of my life, I will ſhewe, that you cannot but giue eare vnto the ſuite, which is now preferred vnto you, though by my baſe and ſinnefull hands, except you will neglect the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of God, ſet light by the ſaluation of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14778:12"/> endanger the ſtate of her Maieſty (whom the Lord long preſerue vnto his glorie) with the whole kingdome, and proclaime vnto the world, that all religion and truth is periſhed from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge you. My manner of dealing herein, as it ſhalbe by the grace of God in all dutie and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; as writing vnto thoſe, whoſe authoritie and places, I am not without great reuerence to conſider, ſo ſhal it be plaine and free without mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing or clipping any part of the trueth (for the feare or fauor of any creature) which it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth you to heare; wherein I will vtter nothing but that, which by the aſſiſtaunce of God, I will ſeale with my blood, if I ſhall be driuen therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. The reaſon moouing me to ſo free and plaine a kind of writing, as neither I dealing in the ſame cauſe, nor yet any els before me haue vſed, is not (the Lord is my witnes) becauſe I would hereby, arrogate vnto my ſelfe, the prayſe of a bolde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buker of ſtates, &amp; great perſonages; but it is firſt, becauſe I deale in that matter, vpon the goodnes whereof, I may preſume to ſpeak the whole truth of God, eſpecially writing vnto an aſſembly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing true religion. Secondly, becauſe the ſuite is put vp vnto them, who although they profeſſe to ſeeke the honor of God: yet haue heretofore altogether vndutifully refuſed to giue the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnto any motion tending vnto the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the religion, which they pretend to fauor and profeſſe. Some of them thinking the cauſe at all not worthie to be delt in. Others, not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſliking the ſuite, iudged notwithſtanding the time wherein it was to be handled, not to be as yet come. Becauſe they ſaw that the baſe and <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14778:12"/> ſupplicatorie maner whereby it deſired the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, made al other cauſes comming with autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from men, to be preferred before it. The moſt who in deede ſincerely fauoreth the cauſe, haue thought it to be a gaineles matter to deale at all therein. For as much as it is the generall voyce of all men, that reformation cannot be taken in hand, without the high and heauie diſpleaſure of her Maieſtie, who (to ſpeake as I am perſwaded) being borne in hand, by the vngodly perſwaſions of ſome godleſſe and irreligious men of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical ſtate, that the Church within her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties dominions, cannot be at a better ſtay then it is; hath not without great reaſon, bene hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hard liar induced to haue the cauſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion againe dealt in, which ſhe is perſwaded al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to be in a tollerable ſort, according to the will of her God. Being alſo vndutifully borne in hand that the endeuour of reforming religion is nothing elſe, but a new fangled and ſeditious attempt, proceeding from the factious &amp; diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented braines of thoſe, who are ſlandered to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereby nothing els, but the alteration of the preſent ſtate, dangerous to her royal crowne and perſon, and ruinous vnto the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. In reſpect whereof, the cauſe offering it ſelfe againe to be conſidered of this high court; it became the ſame to come, with a maieſticall and terrifying countenance; that if it pleaſed the Lorde, it might this way for feare compell them dutifully to ſtoupe vnto it, whoſe fauor and good liking in a peaceable manner, hitherto it coulde by no means procure. And it became it ſo to offer it ſelfe, as withall it might appeare, that the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14778:13"/> of reforming religion, is not a matter tendinge to the diſturbinge of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and the diſliking of her Maieſtie. Except men would ſlanderouſly ſurmiſe the eſtate of this kingdome, to be ſo out of ſquare, as Gods trueth cannot haue paſſage therein, without the immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ruine of al, and ſlanderouſly report her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties will and affection, to be then intollerably croſſed, when the will of her God, is ſought to be eſtabliſhed: which aſſertions, ſhalbe manifeſted to be grieuous, and vndutifull ſlaunders againſt hir Maieſtie and the ſtate; by the opening of ſuch thinges as being amiſſe within Wales, the Lorde requireth to be reformed, at the handes of her Maieſtie and this Parliament.</p>
            <p>The wants therefore, and corruptions of the ſeruice of God in Wales, joyned with the miſery of that people are; firſt, in that the moſt congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations within that countrie, haue all this time of the Goſpell preached in Englande, had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeruice of God, for the working of fayth and repentance ſounding in them, but ſuch, as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the people partaking the ſame, cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be ſaued ordinarily. Miſtake me not. For I doe not ſaye, that eyther that ſeruice, which all this time of her Maieſties gouerment they haue had, and now haue, is idolatrous, or that by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like authoritie of her Maieſtie and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they haue bin publikely enjoyned, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe any other religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then that only true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof alone, ordinary ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be had. But I affirme that God is not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſerued in the moſt aſſemblies there, then that way, whereby the food of eternall life,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14778:13"/> ſhall neuer be ordinarily conuayed to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. This I affirme, and this I will ſtand vnto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for the ſpace nowe of 30. yeares complete, they haue euery where, for the moſt part, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the preaching of the word, without which, as it is plainely ſet downe in manye places of the<note n="a" place="margin">Iam. 1.12. 1 Pet. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Iob. 33.23. 1. Cor. 121. Rom. 10.14. Epheſ. 1.13. and 2.17. Acts. 20.32. Pro. 8.34.35. Iſay. 53.11.</note> word, and I haue elſwhere largely prooued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Maieſtie and this high court, ordinarily, no fleſhe can be ſaued. Now my Lords, and you the reſt of this Parliament, conſider I pray you, what care hath bin had of the ſoules of men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Maieſties gouernement, and how in the dayes of reckoning and account theſe things wil be anſwered. Conſider how lamentable a caſe it is, that in the flowriſhingeſt gouernment for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace, that is again vnder the cope of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; where publike idolatrie hath bene banni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, not one family or one tribe; but a whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould periſhe for want of knowledge. And ſee whether I haue not ſufficient cauſe to deale with you on the behalfe of my countrie. My crie, my crie is not the crie of<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 11.8</note> giltleſſe and innocent blood, which were verye woefull, but of loſt and damned foules, which is moſt lamentable: and giue you eare vnto it, my LL. leaſt the blood of ſoules bee laide to your charge, and required at your hands. For it is not the judiſpenſible du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Parliament to giue eare vnto this crie? Howe then I pray you, will it be anſwered before the judge of all the worlde in the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if you be careleſſe of a dutie ſo neceſſarily required at your handes: when our Sauiour Chriſt affirmed it to be nothing availeable vnto men, to winne the whole worlde,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.22.</note> if they loſe their <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14778:14"/> owne ſoules. Did he thereby thinke you, not only enforce that they are in a miſerable taking, who in reſpect of the knowledge of their ſaluation, know not the right hand from the left: but alſo forcible in feare, that gouernours vnto whome of truſt he hath committed inferiours, diſcharge not their duties in his ſight, vnleſſe they haue great care of the ſaluation of their people? Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe he doth. Let them therefore be afraide of aeternall ſhame and confuſion, who bluſhe not to be buſie in the conſultation of euerye trifling matter, and would be accounted great ſtate men for tything Minte and Cummin, whereas in the meane time, they are not aſhamed, no not to withſtande the conſultation, purpoſing to bring that to paſſe, which the wiſdome of God himſelfe Ieſus Chriſt, hath pronounced to be worthy the whole world, euen the ſauing health of men. Wel the day will come, how ſoone he alone knoweth, in whoſe handes are the keyes of all knowledge; wherein it ſhall appeare by wofull experience, &amp; that too late, what an heauie reckoning will bee made with ſuch Parliament men. And take you heed that are of this aſſembly, now at the length after ſo many warnings, leſt you be found in their number, who make light account of the cauſe of the Goſpell offered vnto them, and who thinke the matter of mens ſaluation, to be nothing elſe but a conceit, wherewith the immaginations of melanchollicke heads are vſually troubled. The cauſe one day ſhalbe found worth the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, howſoeuer men now thinke that they may without dammage ſecurely contemne the ſame. And I woulde humbly intreate this high courte <pb n="13" facs="tcp:14778:14"/> more ſeriouſly to conſider thereof. The ſuite is, that Gods honour may be truely yeelded vnto him by the ſubiectes of this kingdome, and that their ſoules may be ſaued in the daye of Ieſus Chriſt; ſuch a ſuit as a greater cannot be conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of amongſt the ſonnes of men. And will not the wiſeſt and greateſt aſſembly in the land, take order that this may be harkened vnto? Wil they not conſult of a waye how men may come vnto the means whereby they may be ſaued; To what end elſe my Lordes ſhould you be aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, if this cauſe be not handled in your mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings? A Parliament gathered together in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, in the dayes of the Goſpell vnder Queene ELIZABETH, and the cauſe of Gods honor, &amp; the felicitie of the ſubiectes neuer thought vpon, neuer accounted worthy the conſultation. Such a ſtate and ſuch a gouernment may flowriſh and continue in peace for a time: but vndoubtedly the deſtruction therof is decreed with the Lord, the execution of which decree, ſhal not be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long deferred, without ſpeedie repentance. Can there be a meeting of all ſtates in the lande to conſult in Parliament, what may be moſt behof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the promoting of Gods glorye, and the good of the common welth, and yet no care had, how the aeternal miſerie of a whole nation, euen almoſt the fourth part of the kingdome may be preuented? What is this elſe but to dally with Gods honour, and to delude his people of their ſaluation? When eſpecially after ſo many Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments, in a kingdome freely profeſſing the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell for the ſpace of 30. yeares, in the fourth part of the kingdome, there ſhalbe founde ſuch groſſe <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14778:15"/> ignorance, as no region vnder heauen, coulde at anye time yeelde the like preſident, ſo long after the banniſhing of idolatrie. I doe not ſolace my ſelf in conſidering the miſerie of my natiue cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen, neither do I thinke thereof at all, vnleſſe it be to bewaile their eſtate, and to conſider how it may be redreſſed. This I may ſay of them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence, that they neuer as yet for the moſt part, enjoyed the preaching of the Goſpell, ſince they wer profeſſed idolators vnder poperie. Now what felicitie concerning ſpirituall things, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion without the Goſpell preached can haue, the ſame they may enjoye I denie not. But what will be the end of ſuch a profeſſion? verely euen this. After a few dayes miſerably ſpent in this life ſuch profeſſors ſhalbe ſure (for any thing that is otherwiſe reuealed) to liue in hell for euermore. Will it then profit them at all, to haue liued in a kingdome profeſſing true religion, though they haue gayned the whol world therein, ſeeing they are ſure to loſe their owne ſoules: becauſe in this life they haue wanted the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. And if this that I haue ſet downe be not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to expreſſe their miſerie, and to mooue you to conſider of them, I know not what may be accounted miſerable, or what may procure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. Or if this will not mooue you to graunt them the preaching of the Goſpell, then ſhal you leaue vnto poſterities, but a ſmall teſtimonie of your religious hearts, and loue to the Lords ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie. Is there not an heauen my Lordes, after this life for men to goe vnto? Is it poſſible that they ſhall ordinarily go thither, who neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the preaching of the Goſpell? Or can our <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14778:15"/> people in Wales looke for extraordinarie ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? And will not you ſee that they be no longer deſtitute of this meanes, whereby they may walk in the ſtatutes of life and not die? Is this peticion that God may be truly honored, and the ſoules of men ſaued, hurtful to the ſtate, dangerous to her Maieſties ctowne and dignitie, and contrary vnto hir affection? cannot this ſtate ſtand if God ſhould be truly honored, and that people trained in the waies of godlines? Cannot her Maieſties crowne and dignitie ſtand, if theſe thinges be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted in Parliament? And muſt ſhee needs be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifully gainſaid, when the honor of her God, &amp; the bleſſedneſſe of her people are pleaded for? Whoſoeuer haue, do, or will ſlaunder their ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and the whole ſtate, in this vile and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifull ſort, it is pitie they were not ſeuerely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. Againe my LL. is that a religious aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly? Is that an aſſemblie wherein trueth, pietie, the honor of God, and the aeternall happineſſe of men ſhal beare any ſway, where this petition can not be granted? Which deſireth nothing els, but that whiche may be enacted without the great hurt of any, &amp; which ought to be graunted, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer in the judgment of fleſhly wiſe men might ſeeme to enſue thereof. They will neuer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ſight of God and his Churche, eſcape the ignominie and ſtaine of irreligious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane men, whoſe eyes will not be mooued with compaſſion at the eſtate of our people, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Gods ſeruice among them. Nowe if I be thought to haue reported any vntrueth, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their eſtate, let me be brought face to face, for the triall hereof, with thoſe vnto whom the <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14778:16"/> care (I ſhould ſay the ſpoile) of the Church there is committed, and being conuinced to haue vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any vntrueth, let me haue no fauour, but dye the death, before you of this honourable aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye, and my blood be vpon my owne heade, for impeaching the credite of the rulers of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and their gouernement, vndutifully by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like writing, whoſe eſtimation I know it to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for me, euen in thought once to violate.</p>
            <p>I doe here therefore before your Hh. offer to prooue more at large, that the moſt congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Wales, want the very eſpeciall outwarde markes of a Church, and ſo the meanes of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the worde preached, and the comfort of fayth, by the right adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. I alſo offer to prooue, that your Hh. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your ſpeedie repentaunce ſhalbe reckoned with, becauſe that in this point, you haue plowed but iniquitie, and ſowed wickednes, and ſo as Iob ſayth,<note place="margin">Iob. 4.8.</note> you ſhall reape the ſame. Beleeue them not, who tell you that all is well within Wales, &amp; that they are a ſort of clamorous and vndiſcreet men, who affirme the contrary. Beleue them not, who tell you that it belongeth not vnto your duties to be carefull of the eſtate of the Church, and that the Lorde requireth no more at your hands, but the mayntenance of outwarde peace. As though men committed to your gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were but droues of bruite beaſtes, onely to be foddered,<note place="margin">Ie. 17.13.14.</note> and kept from external invaſions and inroods. Giue eare rather vnto the words of the Prophet, who with a loude voyce crieth vnto you; Why will you die, you, your families &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by the ſword, by the famine, and by the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14778:16"/> And why will you be damned (I may alude without injurie vnto the word) as the Lord hath ſpoken againſt all thoſe gouernours, that wil not ſee their people prouided<note n="a" place="margin">Ezra 7.17.23. pſa 2.10. &amp; 101. 2. chr.
29 10. &amp; 30.9 &amp; 34.27. ex. 20.10. gen. 18.19. 2. chr. 15.12.13. &amp;
17.7.</note> for, of the meanes of ſaluation. Therefore heare not the words of the prophets, who tell you, that you ſhall neyther ſee ſword nor famine, though you be ſtill as careles of your people, as hitherto you haue bene. Looke the punniſhments both of flattering prophetes, and of thoſe that are deceiued by their flatterie. Ierem. 14.15. Heare them not I ſay, but obeye the Lord in the execution of that dutie which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteth at your hands, by calling your people to the knowledge of his ſonne, that you may liue. For why ſhould this lande be made deſolate, for this your careleſnes? Ierem.
27.17. They prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie vanitie and lies vnto you, which ſaye peace, peace, while you diſpiſe the Lorde, and walke in this ſecure courſe, or elſe Ieremiah is deceiued. If they be prophets, and if the word of the Lord be in their mouths, let them intreat her Maieſtie, &amp; you of this parliament, that the miſery of helples Wales, may at this time of your meeting be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered off, and redreſſed.</p>
            <p>Thus I haue ſet downe ſome part of the wants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the ſeruice of God in Wales, and ſome part of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat miſerie, wherein my countrie is bewrapped; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd which you are bound vnto the Lord (but by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e moſt humbly entreated) to redreſſe. And this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the cauſe wherein if you deale not, you betray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he honor of God, betraye his trueth, betraye the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eligion which you profeſſe, and betraye her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtie, and the whole kingdome, vnto the reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing hand of God. For without controuerſie, the <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14778:17"/> continuance of our ignorance, and the defectes of Gods ſeruice, will one day, and that ſhortly, I feare me, bring the Lord in fearefull and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming judgementes to take punniſhment of you, your wiues children, families and the wholland: becauſe in your ſtates &amp; conſultation, his honor, and the blood of mens ſouls were not regarded. But this is neyther all the miſerie of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Wales, neythet is this all that the Lorde requireth to be amended by this Parliament, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of his heauie wrath.</p>
            <p>In the ſeconde place then we are to conſider, the corruptions tollerated by the poſitiue lawes of this land, and countenanced by the authority of this high court of Parliament, in the ſeruice of God within Wales. Whereby no ſmall diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor redoundeth vnto the Maieſtie of God, and wherein no ſmall part of the ſpirituall miſerie of that people doth conſiſt. For the remouing of which corruptions, it behoueth the Parliament, with ſpeede to be very carefull, euen before ſuch time as the Lord calleth the land to an account, for the wicked conſtitutions therein maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Here therefore I affirme, vnleſſe without delay you labour to cleanſe the Churche vnder your gouernement in Wales, of all L. Bb. dumbe miniſters, nonreſidents, archdeacons, commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and all other romiſh officers &amp; offices, there tollerated, and ſo tollerated, as by the conſent &amp; authoritie of the Parliament they are maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; that you are both in this life and the life to come, likely to be ſubiecte vnto the intollerable maſſe of Gods wrath, the execution whereof is not vnlikely to fall vpon you and your houſes, <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14778:17"/> vnleſſe you preuent the fiercenes of the Lordes indigna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>If Moſes by a poſitiue lawe, ſhould haue allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the offring of ſtrange fire by Nadab and Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu, tollerated the miniſtery of blemiſhed &amp;<note n="a" place="margin">Leu. 20.18 23.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Leuites, ennacted that one not being of the line of Aaron, might preſſe before the Altar,<note n="b" place="margin">Num. 16.10.18.7.</note> to offer the bread of his God: if Dauid had made it lawfull for Vzzah, to lay his hand vpon the Arke; if Ioſiah or any other the godly rulers had, either giuen leaue to the curſed ſhepheardes in their dayes, to place others in their ſtead, to take<note n="c" place="margin">Ezek. 44.9</note> the ouerſight of the Sanctuary? Or permitted a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated prieſt to be a ciuill gouernour; briefely had eſtabliſhed any thing in the Churche gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſcribed by Moſes, contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, had they not bene in danger of the Lords wrath? They had without controuerſie.</p>
            <p>And ſhall you of the high court of Parliament be diſpenced with, being guilty (except you labor to remoue the dumbe miniſtery, nonreſidence, with the vſurped and Antichriſtian ſeats of L. Bb. &amp;c.) of tollerating &amp; eſtabliſhing greater ſinnes among your people in Wales, in ſteed of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment preſcribed by Ieſus Chriſt? aſſure your ſelues no. I do therefore in this point alſo, for the diſcharge of my dutie and conſcience towardes the Lord, his Church, my countrie, and the whol eſtate of this kingdom, taking my life in my hand
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtifying vnto you, before the Maieſtie of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd before his church that our dumbe miniſters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the callings of our L. Bb. archdea. commiſſ. with al other remnants of the ſacriledge brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the Churche by that Romiſhe ſtrumpet, and <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14778:18"/> now remaining in Wales; are intollerable before the Lorde, and that it is not likely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer you tollerating theſe thinges any longer, ſhall eſcape Gods fierie wrath. The trueth hereof I do briefly make knowne by the reaſons following, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to prooue them more at large, euen vpon the peril of my life, againſt our 4. L. Bb. all their chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, retainers, fauorers and wel willers; whether in eyther of the two vniuerſities of this lande, or in any place els whatſoeuer. Theſe things I offer to prooue againſt M. D. Bridges, who lately in a large volume, hath vndertaken their defence. In which booke of his, he hath offered her Maieſtie &amp; the Parliament moſt vndutifull injurie, by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about for the maintenance of his owne belly, &amp; the belies of the reſt of his coat, to allien at the hears of the loyalleſt ſubiects in the lande, from their moſt carefull prince and gouernours. As though her Maieſtie and this honourable court, ment to turne the edge of the ſword againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who indeed deſerue not to be threatned with the ſcabbord.<note place="margin">Compare pag. 448. of D Bridges his booke with Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. cap. 10. li. 5. cont 3. and you ſhall finde the one to haue writen the verie ſame thing for the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath for the pope</note> Into which booke he hath crammed as plaine poperie for the defence of our Bb. as euer Harding, Saunders, Turrian, Bellarmine, or any other the firebrands and enſigne bearers of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh treaſon againſt her Maieſties crowne, haue brought for the Popes ſupremacie. And for as much as he in that booke, hath both vndertaken the defence of thoſe corruptions, for the tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting wherof, the anger of God hangeth ouer the whole land; and alſo ſhewed himſelfe to be Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitiſh Tobiah, againſt the buylding of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem in Wales, by defending the very breaches &amp; ruins of the Babyloniſh ouerthrow, which by the <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14778:18"/> juſt judgements of God vnder poperie we ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to be the perfecteſt building that Sion can be brought vnto; and ſo by this ſlander withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſaluation (which I doubt not) her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and the parliament wiſhe vnto my country. I haue ſo framed the reaſons following, as they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the very foundation and whole frame of that wicked book &amp; of al others, writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the defence of our eſtabliſhed Church gouernment.</p>
            <p>Now that our dumbe miniſters, nonreſidents, L. biſhops, archdea. &amp;c. are nothing els but an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſinnefull men,<note place="margin">Num. 22.14.</note> riſen vp in ſteed of their fathers the idolatrous Monkes and Fryars, ſtil to augment the fierce wrath of God againſt this land and our gouernors: &amp; that this booke of D. Bridges, and whatſoeuer els hath bin written for their defence, are nothing els, but edicts, trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous againſt God, and ſlanderous to your ſacred gouernment, to defend the ſale and exchange of Church goods, &amp; the very deſtruction of ſouls: to ſpeak al in a word, that both theſe corruptions &amp; their defences, are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned by the Lords own reuealed wil, as things directly againſt the ſame, and the lawes of her Maieſtie, expreſſed in his written word; and therefore not to be tollerated by your authoritie, vnleſſe you thinke that you may tollerate ſinne by your lawes; nor yet once to be ſpoken for or countenaunced, vnleſſe you would plead for Baal, I prooue by theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>That forme of Church gouernement whiche maketh our Sauiour Chriſt inferior vnto Moſes,<note place="margin">Iudg. 6.38.</note> is an impious, vngodly, and vnlawfull gouerment flat contrarye to the worde,<note place="margin">Heb 3 6. Nom. 12.7.</note> and therefore in no caſe to be tollerated by any lawes or authoritie, <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14778:19"/> and the booke or bookes defending the ſame, are vngodly and impious bookes. But our Churche gouernment in Wales, by L. biſhops, archd. dumb miniſters, and other eccleſiaſtical officers (as for nonreſidents, let this one reaſon for all ſerue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; they as much as in them lieth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue the people ouer whome they thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, of the onely ordinarie means of ſaluation, which is the word preached) is ſuch gouerment, as maketh the Lord of life, Ieſus Chriſt inferiour to Moſes, and this booke of D. Bridges, with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bookes of the like arguments doe the ſame. Therfore this gouernment is a gouernment, not to be tollerated by law in any ſtate, vnleſſe men woulde feele Gods heauie judgementes for the ſame, and therefore alſo it is a gouernment moſt pernicious and dangerous, euen in pollicie vnto the ciuil gouernment where it is eſtabliſhed, and this booke or books defending the ſame, are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gody wicked and pernicious bookes, trayterous againſt the Maieſtie of Ieſus Chriſte; crying for vnſufferable vengeance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as tolerate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>The propoſition is not to be doubted off. For is that Church gouernment or bookes to be tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, which make Chriſt Ieſus the ſonne of the aeternall God, yea God himſelfe inferiour vnto Moſes? The aſſumption is thus prooued. That gouernement, and that booke or bookes, whiche holdeth Ieſus Chriſt God and man, to haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed no externall forme of the gouernment o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Churche; but ſuch, as at the pleaſure of the magiſtrate, when time and place requireth may be altered without ſinne; preferreth Moſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Ieſus Chriſte. This is manifeſt out of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14778:19"/> wordes of the text. Heb. 3.2.6. Becauſe the Lord Ieſus, being the ſonne, is in that place com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Moſes a faithfull ſeruant in deed, and preferred before Moſes, in regard of the external gouernment, which Moſes had ſo faythfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed vnder the law, as it was not to be chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged at the pleaſure of any magiſtrate, vntill<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 9.27.</note> the Meſſiah ſhould cauſe the oblations to ceaſe. For what king was there euer in Iudah, who without the breach of Gods law,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 23.24.</note> could alter the external regiment of the Iewiſh Church in the Leuitical prieſthood and officers? Dauid I grant, ordained ſome things not mentioned in the bookes of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but that whiche he did, proceeded from the ſpirit of God, and he had the worde for his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. The ſame is to be ſaide of whatſoeuer was done by any other of the godly kings in Iudah.</p>
            <p>Nowe that the former compariſon, Heb. 3.2.6. betweene the ſonne and the ſeruant, Chriſte and Moſes, is concerning the externall regiment of the church, and not the ſpiritual gouernment of the inner man (as D. Bridges affirmeth pag. 51. lin 30.) it is plaine. Becauſe Moſes had nothing to do with the gouerning of the inner man; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were no prerogatiue for the Lorde to be preferred in faithfulnes before Moſes, in that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation wherein Moſes neuer dealt. Hence the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I aſſume, that our forme of Church gouernment in Wales, and this wicked booke, holdeth Ieſus Chriſt to haue ordained ſuch an externall forme of gouernment in his Churche, at his departure from earth to heauen, as at the pleaſure of the magiſtrate, might be altered without the breach of Gods inſtitution: which thing D. Bridges affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14778:20"/> pag. 55. And all our prelates grant that this high court of parliament may lawfully alter the forme of Church gouernement now eſtabliſhed. Therefore this gouernment, and this booke, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth Moſes before Ieſus Chriſt. And I cannot ſee how far this differeth from blaſphemie. Now if Chriſt ſhould be ſaide to ordaine no externall regiment at all, then Moſes is far before him, and the thirſt of ſuperioritie in our prelates, and their accompliſſes, is turned into extreame drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of impietie by this aſſertion.</p>
            <p>I beſeech the Lord in mercy to open your eies that are of this aſſemblie, that you may ſee how he and his people haue been dealt with by retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch laws in force, as juſtle &amp; ouerthrow the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prerogatiue of his ſonn. And the Lord make you to ſee whether thoſe men, that defend the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the ſonn of God in this point againſt the tiranicall vſurpation of Bb. and haue brought for his title vnanſwerable euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, out of the ſacred records of Gods owne writings, offending eyther in matter or circumſtance in no one thing, but that they haue not dealt more earneſtlie with your Hh. and more roundly with the aduerſaries in the right of their maſter; haue deſerued to be impriſoned, thruſte out of their liuinges, reuiled, &amp; railed vpon by vngodly and wicked prelats vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtate, as ſeditious and diſcontented men with the ciuil gouernment, dangerous ſubiectes &amp; enimies vnto her Maieſties crown. And ſurely the cauſe being made knowne vnto you, as nowe it is, how ſoeuer the Lord may beare with your ouerſight heretofore, in the ignoraunce of the waight thereof: yet if you doe not, nowe abrogate <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14778:20"/> ſuch a church gouernment, well may you hope for the fauour and intertainement of Moſes, that is the curſe of the lawe: but the fauoure and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing countenaunce of Ieſus Chriſt, I doe not ſee how you ſhal euer enjoy. To proſecute this point a litle farther. In moſt humble manner, I would know of you that are of this high court, whether of theſe 2. pointes following you would be ſaid to maintain, by the continuance of the aforeſaid cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings &amp; corruptions within Wales? For of either of the 2. you muſt needes be guiltie. Firſt doe you think you may preſume to defend by your autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and lawes, ſuch offices and officers in the eccleſiaſtical ſtate, whereby the churche is to be gouerned; that is, ſuch a Church gouernment, as in your conſciences you cannot, but acknowledg to be vnlawful before the Lord, and hurtful vnto his Church? Secondly doe you thinke that any Church gouernment can be lawfull before your God, and profitable vnto his church, which the Lord Ieſus Chriſt himſelf hath not preſcribed in his word? The which point whoſoeuer goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to defend, he, as before you haue hard, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Ieſus Chriſt, who as he is the onely head of his churche, ſo he hath the alone juriſdiction to ordaine the gouerment therof, not to haue in the gouerment of his owne houſe, as great a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue as Moſes had. I earneſtlie intreat you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that as you would not be accounted, ether to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thoſe things which in your owne conſciences are ſinful, or to account ſuch a Church gouernment to be lawful, as cannot ſtand with the roiall ſouerainty, that Ieſus Chriſt hath in his church: ſo to ſee the ſpedy aboliſhing <pb n="26" facs="tcp:14778:21"/> of al dumbe miniſters Lorde Biſhops, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, commiſſaries, chauncellors, &amp;c. Out of the church, vnder your gouernment in Wales. You are now intreated to abrogate no other Church gouerment then that, which either in your own conſciences you muſt acknowledg to be vnlawful and odious in the ſight of God, and therfore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay to be remoued, or ſuch a regiment the vnlawefulnes whereof, if with our Biſhops you ſhould go about to maintaine, then ſhould you rob Ieſus Chriſt of the prerogatiue &amp; priueledge wherwith the ſpirit of God hath adorned him. Heb. 3.6. Becauſe it hath ben ſhewed, that it was not lawful for any ſtate or power to ordaine any other forme of gouernment in the church vnder the lawe, then that preſcribed by Moſes. If then you think our church gouernment by Lord Bb. Archdeacons, dumb miniſters, &amp;c: in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to be vnlawful, that is; if you think it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for a miniſter, to ioine the office of a ciuil Magiſtrate with his miniſterie, and to beare rule and dominion ouer his bretheren either as a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or temporal Lord; if you think it vnlawfull for a Lord Biſhop to beare ſoueraigne authoritie of al the miniſters within his dioceſſe; and if you think it vnlaweful that their miniſterie with the execution thereof, ſhould depend vpon his ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or diſliking; if alſo in your conſcience you think it vnlawful for him to take the charge of al the ſoules within 4. or 5. ſhires, and to take the charge of thoſe mens ſoules, whoſe faces for the moſt part, he wel knoweth he ſhal neuer behold; if in like mannet you think it vnlawfull for an Archdeacon, whoſe name and office was neuer <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14778:21"/> read of in the word, and in his beſt inſtitution is, but to atend vpon the miniſters and looke vnto the poore (to haue a great number of miniſters at his becke and controlment) or if you think it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful in your ſoules and conſciences, for our dumb miniſters, the patrons of al ignorance and blindenes, to take vpon them the office of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of Ieſus Chriſt, to declare his will vnto the people, the beſt, part wherof, they them ſelues neuer know: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no queſtion to be made, but that either you wil vtterly raze the memorie of this wicked and vngodly generation out of the Churche of Wales, or openly manifeſt, vnto men and angels, that you will to the contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſhonor of your God, and the vndoing of his church, countenance and maintaine L. Biſhops, Archdeacons, dumbe miniſters, with the reſt of that vngodly race, whoſe corruptions in youre owne conſciences you cannot but deteſt. On the other ſide, if you think it lawful for you, to ordain, what forme of church gouernment you like beſt of: and ſo holde it lawful to maintaine this eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed among vs; then ſee what wil follow the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhinge of the prerogatiue that Ieſus Chriſt hath in the gouernment of his church. And that I feare me wil be this. The Lord will enter into iudgement with you of this parliament, for al the ſoules that hereafter ſhal be damned in Wales. Becauſe you make it lawfull by your authority, for ſuch guides to be ouer your people, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſiblie lead, and direct them in the waies of godlines and ſaluation. He wil enter into judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with you for al the ſinnes that ſhalbe there commited, for want of gouerment, which his ſon <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14778:22"/> Chriſt hath ordained as a meanes to keepe men from tranſgreſſing againſt their God. He will enter into judgment with you for the monſtrous profanation, whereby thoſe proude, pope like, and blinde guides, haue polluted his houſe in the dayes of your gouernment, which you ſhoulde haue withſtood. He wil enter in to judgmnt with you for the puniſhments that are likely to fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, becauſe you haue countenanced, and freely priueleadged them by lawe, to prouoke his wrath in that greuous ſort againſt their own ſouls. He wil alſoe (it is to be feared) enter into judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the whol land, for this your ſinne, and make his ſword drunk with the bloud of our ſlain men, yea he wil giue the whole kingdom, high &amp; and lowe, into the handes of the enemie, that is cruel and skilful to deſtroy, that all the nations vnder heauen profeſſing religion, may feare and take heed, howe they doe not only denye to be gouerned by the lawes of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, but which is more grieuous in ſtead thereof, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhe ſuch inſtitutions as are directly againſt his maieſties reuealed will. If thoſe thinges be not likely to fall vppon vs, except the aboue menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned vnlawfull callings of Lord Bb. dumbe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, &amp;c. be now at once euen in this Parliament rooted out of the churche in Wales, let not my head go to the graue in peace. Where are they now, who vſually affirm the intent or motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing L. Bb. dum miniſters, ye the whol church gouerment eſtabliſhed in wales, to be a matter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious in the ſight of her Maieſtie, &amp; dangerous to the ſtate? Cannot hir Maieſty abide to heare, that Chriſt Ieſus ſhould be more faythful in his owne <pb n="29" facs="tcp:14778:22"/> houſe, then Moſes was? Is it an odious hearing vnto her Maieſtie, that the churche in her king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhould be cleanſed of al vnlawful callings and corruptions, and beutified, with the holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of her ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, euen in her daies; that the ſame praiſe might be trulie aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto hir, in the adges to come, which the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God hath yeeled vnto King Ioſiah.<note place="margin">2. Kin. 23.25.</note> Like vnto Queene Elizabeth was there no Queene before hir, that turned vnto the Lord with all hir hart, with all her ſoule, and with al hir might, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all the lawe of Moſes, neither after hir aroſe ther any like vnto hir. Cannot hir Maieſtie I ſay abide theſe things? Far be it that any ſhould perſwade them ſelues ſhe cannot. Then are they vndutiful ſlaunderers of hir highnes, who to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the Parliament from dealing, concerninge the redreſſe of the church, vſually avouch ſuch purpoſes, to be altogether vaine, becauſe hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie will neuer be induced to yeeld hir conſent vnto the remouing of the eſtabliſhed gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church; neither is the ſlaunder any whit leſſe vndutifull againſt the eſtate, when the kingdome is ſaid to be indangered, except Ieſus Chriſt, ſhould make it lawfull for the Parliament to tollerate what Church gouernment the ciuill ſtate can beſt away with. And it is a point wherin you of this Parliament may ſhew what harts you beare vnto the ſinceritie of religion. My 2. reaſon followeth.</p>
            <p>That forme of Church gouernment, and that booke or bookes, which make the eſtabliſhed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment to be an humaine conſtitution, that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſiuely according to the worde (but no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14778:23"/> according to the worde then the ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement is, whiche alſo muſt<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13 2. Pet. 2.10.</note> bee incluſiuely according to the ſame,) and ſo may at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of man bee altered, as the ciuill gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may: that gouernment and that booke or bookes, (beſides that they prefer Moſes before Ieſus Chriſt) is a wicked and pernicious gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Pag. 55.</note> and they vngodly and peſtelent bookes.</p>
            <p>But our Church gouernment in Church cauſes, and this booke of D Bridges with al other books of this grieſte, make the eccleſiaſticall gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be nothing elſe, but an humane conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, which may be lawfully altered, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed at the magiſtrates pleaſure. Therefore our Church gouernment in Wales, and this booke or bookes, are vngodly and wicked.</p>
            <p>The propoſition is proued by theſe reſons. Firſt they are wicked and intollerable, becauſe they make no difference between that which belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the true worſhip of God, as eccleſiaſticall gouernment doth, and that which apertaineth vnto ciuil pollicie. Contrarie to the apoſtle Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who affirmeth in expreſſe wordes, that wee haue reaceaued by the knowledge of God, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer belongeth vnto true religion, in ſuch ſort as it is vnlawful for man to add any thing of his owne inuention therevnto. For ſoe the worde <hi>Euſebeia</hi> tranſlated, godlines, ſignifieth in that place. Whereas the worde hath not ſo furniſhed vs, with whatſoeuer belongeth to the ciuil magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie, called<note n="b" place="margin">Pet. 3.13.</note> mans ordinaunce by the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, but that therein thoſe thinges, that haue been and are inuented by them that neuer knew God, are warrantable, and may be incluſiuely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14778:23"/> to the word. Secondly eccleſiaſticall gouernment being granted to be an human con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, maketh the Pope to haue ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant out of the word,<note place="margin">If you read D. Bridges pag. 448. lin 3 you ſhall finde him not far from auouching this point.</note> not of his Idolatrous and falſe religion, but of his ſuperioritie, ouer all ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil Maieſtrates and paſtors within the eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal bodie of the church. For whie ſhould not the pope the ciuill Maieſtrate granting him this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie, as all they vnder his juriſdiction doe) be alowed by the word, to be aboue the emperor, and all other Magiſtrates and miniſters whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, if the eccleſiaſticall gouernment be an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ordinance? For I am aſſured that the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, with al other princes in Europe, may lawfully chuſe a Magiſtrate ſuperior vnto them all, if they wil. And why may not this magiſtrate whom they may lawfully chuſe (and he lawfully yeelde vnto their choyſe) to be the higheſt and ſuperiour go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or in chriſtendome, to be a biſhop, or an archb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Church gouernement be an humane ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, or if it be lawfull for either of them to be Lordes, and to beare a ciuill office? Before I goe farther, I am particularly in this poynt, to deale with ſuch in this parliament, as are our L. Bb. in Wales. Here therefore in the audience of her R. excellent Maieſtie, and this honorable councel, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prooue before you the B. of Landaff, Dauids, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aph and Bangor, that the Pope of Rome, whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uperioritie all ſounde hearted chriſtians doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nowledge to be intollerable and accurſed, hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ltogether as good warraunt from the worde for his eccleſiaſticall hierarchie, as you, vnto whom I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow ſpeake, to be L. biſhops in Wales. My reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conclude after this manner; and if you can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14778:24"/> anye part thereof, I will not refuſe anye death, or other puniſhment, that ſhalbe laide vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me. What Bb. ſoeuet they be, that haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther warrant of their lordly juriſdiction, whereby they exerciſe temporal gouernment, as ciuil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, hauing ſtill their miniſtery vpon them, &amp; claime vnto themſelues ſuperiority ouer their felow brethren, as miniſters, then the ordinance, good will and pleaſure of man, that is, of the ſtate wherin they liue; they haue no better warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the word of god, for this their lordly ſuperiority, then the Pope of Rome hath for his, who clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth no other juriſdiction and ſuperioritie vnto himſelfe, ouer magiſtrats and miniſters, then that which he hath, by the free conſent, good liking, and authoritye of thoſe ſtates, who voluntarilye ſubmit themſelues vnto his idolatrous religion. But you the Bb. of Landaff, Davids, Bangor, and Aſſaph in Wales, haue no other warrant to be L. biſhops, that is, to joyne both magiſtracie and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie together, and claime vnto your ſelues authority ſpirituall (in deed according to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite that ruleth in the ayre, as the Apoſtle ſayth) ouer your fellowe miniſters, then the conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of man, to witt; the will and pleaſure of her Maieſty and this high court of parliament. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you the ſaid L. biſhopps, haue no other war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for your Lordſhips and ſuperioritie ouer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miniſters, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pope hath for his ſupream authoritie, and vniverſall prerogatiue. As for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> crueltie, pride, and idolatrous profeſſion; far be it but I ſhould make difference betweene you an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him. Although euery part of this reaſon be alrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy prooued; yet I demand of you, by what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14778:24"/> you are ſo far, in reſpect of temporal things, and the abuſe of eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before many godly and learned miniſters in this land; as you by vertue of your places, are Barons of the parliament houſe, enjoye great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venews, and are Lordes ouer your brethren and fellow miniſters? Your anſwere will be I knowe, that you hold this by the ſole authoritie of man, and no otherwiſe. This muſt needs be your aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. For if you woulde claime your juriſdiction by any other title, your biſhoppricks would ſoone be forfeited. Now I pray you tell me, hath not the pope as good warraunt for his hierarchie as this is? For hath not the Emperor, the king of Spain, the Frenche king, with other ſtates, now profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing poperie, as good allowance from the worde, in regard of the office (as for the abuſe in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or religion, that is not the queſtion) to make whom they will the ſuperior B. within their owne dominions, as her Maieſtie and the parliament hath to make one of you to be aboue al the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in your dioces, or as good warraunt as they might haue to make eyther of you, to be Primate and Metropolitane ouer the reſt; which authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie you will not denie vnto them, as vnlawfull I am ſure. Eyther therefore, the ſuperiour power of the pope in his vniuerſal biſhoppricke, is a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſuperioritie, or els your lordſhips hauing no better warrant from the word, then the popedom hath; are vnlawfull, and intollerable. And it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnlawfull for the parliament to tollerate, and countenance (I doe not ſay the popiſhe religion) but his ſuperiority ouer the miniſters within this land; it is alſo as vnlawful for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to tollerat your <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14778:25"/> ſpirituall juriſdiction ouer your fellow brethren. Here then I appeale vnto your conſciences, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you doe not ſee that the pope hath altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as good allowaunce from the worde, of his Antichriſtian juriſdiction, as you haue of your lordly callings. And againe I appeale vnto you, whether you, who dare not, but holde the pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the B. of Rome to be an vnlawfull juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; do not you thinke, that the pope (though hee profeſſed the trueth of religion, as you doe, which in the dayes of the firſt biſhopps of Rome they alſo did) were not bounde in conſcience, to giue ouer this vniuerſall ſoueraigntie? Or if he coulde not abide to heare, that his place and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, whiche by the poſitiue law, and the good ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the preſent gouernement, were authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſhoulde nowe be accounted vnlawfull in the ſight of God; do you not thinke that hir Maieſty, and this high court of parliament, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the lawes eſtabliſhed, and the fauour they beare vnto his juriidiction, were bounde before the Lorde, to abrogate his ſuperioritie, as vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and intollerable in Gods Church. If you thus judge of the pope, as I hope you do! Oh then, why wil not you execute this ſentence againſt your ſelues, whiche you haue pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced againſt him? you beeing no leſſe guiltie of tyrannizing ouer your brethren, by vertue of your vnlawful cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. The juriſdiction of the pope is vnlawful (ſay you) notwithſtanding all the ſtates in Europe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him to be vniverſall biſhop, and it is vnlawful notwithſtanding poperie were true religion, and hee a moſt holy man who ſate in the Romiſhe chaire. And you holde it alſo vnlawfull for the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14778:25"/> parliament, notwithſtanding al the former excep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, to tollerate the popiſh ſupremacie, euen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the miniſters in this land. Why the worde of God by the ſame reaſon, pronounceth your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to be vnlawful, and denieth it to be poſſible for them to be lawfull and tollerable, no though her Maieſtie and al the ſtates and parliaments in the world ratified them to be lawful.</p>
            <p>To returne againe vnto the whole bodie of this honourable aſſemblye. I intreate you in the name of God to conſider, how prejudiciall it wil be for our poſterities to refuſe the popes juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction (if euer motion ſhould be made in parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the reducing of that man of ſinne, as God forbidd there ſhoulde) ſeeing you haue not thought it vnlawful to retain their Ll. &amp; ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, who haue no better warrant for their calling then the pope might haue for his, beeing confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the free conſent of the ſtate. I go forward.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if Church gouernment be an humane conſtitution, then it may be lawfull for a church gouernour, vz. a biſhopp, archdeacon, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that order, to preache, adminiſter the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, ouerſee, excommunicate, &amp;c. and to be a king. For the holy Ghoſte maketh it lawful, 1. Pet. 2.13. for any, ſupplying the place of an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane conſtitution lawfully, to be a king. And I woulde our biſhopps durſt denie it? Where then learne they that diuinitie, that it is more againſt the word, for a biſhop to be <hi>Baſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eus,</hi> a king, <hi>Hyperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chon,</hi> a ſuperiour, <hi>Hegemon,</hi> a captaine or gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, being titles<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13</note> ſanctified by the holy Ghoſte for ciuill officers, then <hi>Curios</hi> a Lord, <hi>Hyperpheron,</hi> a prelate,
<hi>Euergetes,</hi> a lords grace. The former and <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14778:26"/> latter, vz. <hi>Curios</hi> &amp; <hi>Euergetes,</hi> being denied by our Sauiour<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 22.25</note> Chriſte vnto biſhopps or miniſters, the 2. vz. <hi>Hyperpheron,</hi> neuer red in the word, for ought that I can remember. If they ſaye, that the abuſe of Lordlines, and graceles grace is forbidden by Chriſte, they haue bene anſwered, they are aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, and let them replye when they can; that our Sauiour Chriſt neuer alowed abuſe or tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in ciuill gouernors, when as he doth not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them to rule as Lordes, or to be called grace; and therefore ſpeaketh in this place, Luk.
22.25. of the lawful and ſanctified vſe of ciuil gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and titles, which ſanctified vſe being lawful in the ciuil magiſtrates, he denieth to be lawful in his miniſters. He denieth I ſaye, the vſe both of the name and title of the magiſtracie, and alſo of the office vnto his miniſters. Becauſe it were pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable abſurd, to thinke that the Lord in deed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth his miniſters to beare the name and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the magiſtrats, whereas he granteth them the office and dignitie, wherevnto that name or title may be lawfully joyned in the ciuil magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. Here I knowe that the example of Ely the high prieſtes ciuill gouernment, will be brought in for the confirmation of the ciuil authoritie of our biſhops; wherevnto I wil make no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer at this time, but that I hope that our biſhops do not thinke, that we vnder her Maieſties raign and peaceable gouernment, are brought to that exigencie, which the prophet threatneth ſhould come vpon the people of Iudah:<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.6.</note> namely, that we ſhoulde take holde of ſome biſhop, and ſaye, thou ſhalt be our gouernour, becauſe we meane that our fall and ouerthrow ſhalbe vnder thine hand.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14778:26"/> For when Ely joyned the ciuil gouerment of the Iewes with his prieſthood, then the philiſtims gaue the Iewes a ſhameful ouerthrow, and tooke away the Arke of God. So that vnleſſe we holde it lawful for vs to ſeeke ſuch meanes, as wherby we ſhal be ſure to fal before our enemies, and to be bereaued of the Arke of God; I ſee not why the example of Ely (who to make the beſt of it, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſome extraordinarye thing proper vnto Ely, and not to bee drawen into example by others) ſhould make it lawful for miniſters to beare ciuil offices. For in deed it ſheweth nothing els for our inſtruction, but that a readie way to bring a final deſtruction vpon the land, is, for the parliament to giue our miniſters leaue to joyn the magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie &amp; the miniſtery together. And here it woulde be knowne, whether they (whoe in their bookes haue whotly and egerly purſued this example of Ely, to defend the ciuill juriſdiction of miniſters) haue not therein ſome ſecret meaning, if oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie woulde ſerue, to aſpire vnto the crowne. For they may be ſuſpected to hope, if euer an
<hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erregium</hi> ſhould fall (as I truſt in God it ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be in their dayes) that the eſtate would think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t moſt convenient, to commit the ſoueraigntie vnto ſom conſcionable Churchman, vntill it may be otherwiſe diſpoſed off. And therefore it may be juſtly ſuſpected, that in diſputing from the example of Ely, they had one eye vnto this wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I ſpeak. For they may procue far better by the example of Ely, who was the chiefe magiſtrate in his dayes, that a miniſter may joyne a whol king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnto his miniſterie, rather then any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nferiour office.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14778:27"/>To conclude this point. Seeing, Firſt to make that which belongeth to the outwarde worſhip of God, to haue no more ground out of the worde, then that which appertaineth vnto the ciuil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie. Secondly, to allowe of the popes ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritie as lawful. And thirdly, to holde that a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may be both a king and a miniſter, are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and abſurd aſſertions, and as we ſee directly againſt the word. Therefore it is wicked in like maner, to make the eccleſiaſtical gouerment to be an humane conſtitution: and not vnlikely by little and little, to paue the way for the vndermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ciuil gouernement; as the reaſons which our Bb. do bring for the maintenaunce of their ſuperioritie, and experience vnder poperie do giue vs juſt cauſe to ſuſpect. For why may not a forged donation of Conſtantine, or Lodouicus pius, in time joyne the crowne of England, to the ſea of Davids or Bangor eſpecially; whiche from Ioſeph of Aramathea, can be prooued to haue a little better continuance of perſonall ſucceſſion, then Rome can from Peter; as well, as it joyned the kingdome of Sicilia, the Dukedome of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, the Ilandes, Corſica; Sardinia, &amp;c: vnto the popes Miter.</p>
            <p>The thirde reaſon is thus framed, and I will be briefe. That forme of Church gouernement, and that booke or bookes, which teacheth, that there is ſomething to be obſerued, beſides that, which was included in the commiſſion giuen by our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt vnto his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Math. 28.19</note> wherin they were enjoyned to teache men, to obſerue whatſoeuer he commanded, is a gouernement execrable and accurſed by the ſpirite of God in plaine wordes, <pb n="39" facs="tcp:14778:27"/> Gal. 1.9: and ſo are the bookes. And being ſuch, far beit, that eyther the gouerment, or the books ſhoulde be maintained by the authoritie of this high court of parliament. Such a curſe being pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounced againſt the maintaining of execrable things, as we finde Deuter. 7.15. But our forme of church gouernement in Wales, and this booke with many others, publiſhed by authoritie teach the ſame. For where is it included, much leſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the word, that our Sauiour Chriſt abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed an outward gouernment of the Church in the Leuitical pollicy, being in no ſort an humane ordinance, but altogether preſcribed by the lord himſelfe, to the end, that vnder the Goſpel there ſhould be no gouernement of the Church but an humane ordinance, that might lawfully be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged at the pleaſure of man? Or where is it reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that the Apoſtles gaue the ciuill magiſtrate, when any ſhould be in the Churche; the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to aboliſhe the Preſbytery by them eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; becauſe there was no chriſtian magiſtrate in the Churche, as our aduerſaries themſelues confeſſe: but as the worde ſayth,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.5 11. ephe. 4.4 rom. 12.6. 1. pet.
4.10 math. 21 25.</note> eſtabliſhed by the Lorde; and therefore not to be abrogated by the magiſtrate, vntill his pleaſure in that poynte be farther knowne: therefore this gouernment, &amp; this book or books, are execrable &amp; accurſed.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, that forme of Church gouernement, &amp; that booke or books, which affirme the kingdom of Chriſte in the outwarde gouernement, to be a kingdome that cann be ſhaken, that is, altered, or remooued as the ceremoniall gouernement was: affirme that, which is contrarye to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe written word of God. Heb. 12.28. and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14778:28"/> are not to be tollerated. But our Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment in Wales by L. Bb. archdea. dumb mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, commiſſ. &amp;c, in their making of miniſters, excommunication, &amp;c: is ſuch, and ſuche is this vnlearned heape and ſophiſticall booke, with the reſt written on this argument. And therefore both the booke or bookes, affirme things contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the worde, and ſo are not to be tollerated, vnleſſe we would haue the Lorde to bring ſpeedie ſhame and confuſion vppon vs, for mayntaining ſinne by lawe.</p>
            <p>The propoſition is apparant. Becauſe that by the word kingdome that cannot be ſhaken in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foerſaid place. Heb. 12.28. muſt needes be ment perticularly (whatſoeuer ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> els thei haue as more generall) the outward gouernment eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed vnder the Goſpel, ſince the aboliſhing of the ceremoniall lawe, which being compared, in regard of continuance, and remouing or doing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie with Moſes his gouernment, (is ſaide to be a kingdome that cannot be ſhaken) that is, ſuch as the Lorde neuer meaneth to alter again vnto the worlds end: as to haue any other gouernment placed in ſtead thereof by himſelfe, much leſſe by man, wheras that vnder Moſes is affirmed by the prophet Haggaie,<note place="margin">Haggai 2.7.</note> and heare by the apoſtle, to be a kingdom or gouernment that could be ſhaken, that is, altered. And this is the proper meaning of the place, Heb. 12.28. For by the kingdome that cannot be ſhaken, muſt needes be meant, either the aſſurance of ſaluation, which we haue vnder the Goſpel, or our inioying and profeſſing of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, or elſe the outwarde gouernement, not only in the preaching of the word, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration <pb n="41" facs="tcp:14778:28"/> of the ſacraments, but in the Church officers, the manner of their choiſe &amp; their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ects, wherin they are to be occupied. But as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning aſſurance of ſaluation in this life, &amp; the profeſſion of eternal life in heauen, which the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers enioyed vnder the lawe, it was no more to be ſhaken then ours, the meanes thervnto by the word preached, they want no more then we doe. And ſo in theſe reſpectes they had a kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat could no more be ſhaken then ours. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth therefore, that theirs was to be ſhaken, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n regarde of their outward gouernment, which was aboliſhed by the comming of Chriſt. And
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore ours immooueable in this reſpect, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>il his ſecond comming, which were ſenſleſſe to be affirmed, if Chriſt in his kingdome, wherevnto we are ſubiect, had inſtituted no externall regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Churche. Can that be vnmooueable which is not at all? More ſenſeles it were to think, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his kingdom to be immutual in regard of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and not of the perſons, and officers, who are to deale with thoſe miſteries.</p>
            <p>To come againe vnto you of this honourable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourt of Parliament, you are not to learne, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o defend, by lawe, or to countenance by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, the breach of gods ordinance is the defence of ſin, and that the defence of ſinne, is the hatred of God, who rewardeth them to their faces that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate him, Deut. 7.10. and therefore alſo you are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot to be taught, what horrible ſinnes you ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommit,<note place="margin">Nomb. 26.9.</note> if hereafter you ſtil maintaine ſuch plain &amp; manifeſt impieties. They are no trifles as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee. For I aſſure you, that Dathan and Abiram <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſonnes of Eliab, men famous in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14778:29"/> had more colour of right, to claime vnto themſelues either the ciuill gouernement from Moſes, or the prieſthood from Aharon. Becauſe they were the ſonnes of Reuben the firſte borne (vnto whoſe lotte, had he not defiled his fathers<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 49.4.</note> bedd, by all likelihood, either the ſcepter or the prieſthood ſhould haue fallen) then theſe vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers haue to claim the places they are in, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto either by right of inheritance according to the fleſh, or ordinaunce from God, they came by no title.</p>
            <p>Here it muſt needes followe (you of this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable aſſemblie hauing regarde vnto the eſtate of your ſoules and bodies before the Lord, and your good names amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g poſterities) that if theſe things ſet downe be true (if not bring vppon me deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſhame and puniſhment) you wil either labor to redres the miſerable eſtate of diſtreſſed wales, by erecting there a godly miniſterie, and abolliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Cananitiſhe relikes, or for the defence, of a fewe vnconſcionable and godleſſe men, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to vndergoe the fierie and flaming exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, of the burning decree of Gods wrath: My Lords, and you the reſt of this aſſemblie, be not deceiued, the Lord of heauen is angrie with you and his whole hoaſt for the Babiloniſh garments of theſe Achanes.<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.9.21</note> Retayne them no longer if you would not fall before the enemie. When the L. ſhall plead with you, your wiues, children, family, &amp; the whole land,<note place="margin">Ezek.
38.22.</note> with peſtilence or with blood, as he is likely to do for theſe wedges of execrable golde, it is not the pontificall Lordſhips of Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops, at whoſe commaundement the Lords ſword wil returne again into his ſheath, when your gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <pb n="43" facs="tcp:14778:29"/> ſoules ſhal cry for mercy at the Lords hand; it is not the proud and popelike Lordſhipps of Biſhopps, their vſurped juriſdictions, their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane excommunications, their pitiles murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſoules, their railinge ſlaunders, againſt Gods truth and his ſeruants, their impious bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the holy Ghoſt vpon their Idol prieſtes, that wil driue the Lord to giue you any comfort. Let me therfore (thogh my perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be baſe) entreat you, that the judgments of God againſt ſin, both in this life, &amp; in that other of eternal wo &amp; miſery may apeare ſo terible in your eies, and of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douted conſequence, as you wil no longer retain vnder your gouernment theſe things, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance do giue the Lord juſt cauſe in this life to pronounce this ſentence by the mouth of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie againſt euerie on of you,<note place="margin">Iere. 22.29.</note> that wil not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote this ſute, and execute the ſame. O earth, earth, earth, here the wordes of Iehouah, write theſe men deſtitute of children, men that ſhall not proſper in their dayes, yea there ſhal not bee a man of their ſeed that ſhall proſper, and bee a-parliament man, or beare rule in England any more. And in the life to come to ſay moreouer: Theſe mine enemies that would not haue me to beare rule,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.27.</note> by mine owne lawes ouer them and their people, bring hither &amp; ſlay before my face, yea bind them hand and foote, and throw them to vtter darknes, there is weeping &amp; gnaſhing of teth. And let me, crauing vpon my knees, with all ſubmiſſion and earneſtnes, and more earneſt if it were poſſible to obtane, that my countrymen by your meanes may haue the word preached, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the meanes whereby they may liue for euer, <pb n="44" facs="tcp:14778:30"/> with Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, in the kingdome of heauen. Graunt them this my Lordes, though I dye for it. And this the Lord knoweth is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcope of my writing, and not the diſcrediting or galling of our Lorde Bb. Let not their places withſtand the ſaluation of my brethren, and the true ſeruice of God among them, and if euer I ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther write or ſpeake more againſt them, any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then their places, are like to be the ruine of hir Maieſtie and the whole ſtate, let it coſt me my life. Here me in this ſute good my Ll. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thereof, your ſoules ſhall find; otherwiſe I am likelie to become a weariſom and an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate ſutor vnto this high aſſemblye. The cauſe is ſo juſte, that if it were as ſometimes it was, by the apoſtle him ſelfe decided in the Athenianes Areopago, a court for heathen juſtice of famous and celebrated memory, I doubt not but it ſhould be hard. And ſhal it not haue juſtice in the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an parliament of England; Iuſtice my Lords I ſay, for I ſeeke nothing elſe, but that the ſtatutes of the God of judgment and juſtice may be made known in my country, wher now they are vnhard of. Then the which, I know not what can be more juſt; neither can I ſee what juſtice in truth can be adminiſtred by them that neglect this cauſe. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for mine owne parte, God aiding me, I wil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer leaue the ſuite; though there ſhoulde bee a thouſand parliaments in my dayes, vntill I ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obtaine it at your handes, or bring the Lord in vengeance and bloud to plead againſt you, for repelling his cauſe. I hope it wil not be here ſaid, that the parliament can doe nothing in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe hytherto all Churche cauſes haue
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14778:30"/> bin referred vnto the conuocation houſe &amp; the leaders thereof, namelie to our Biſhops. And doe you meane it ſhalbe ſo ſtill? Then ſhall you ſtill maintain theſe horrible profanations of Gods ſanctuarie, whereof I haue ſpoken. Then may it be ſaid vnto your ſhame, that Sion lying vppon the ground, and mourning like a widdow, ſtretched out her handes vnto the parliament of England, but could find no comfort. Then may you ſtil be ſaid to betray Gods truth, to betray the ſaluation of his people, yea and to betray the liberties of this parliament. For what aſſembly is there in the land, that dare chaleng vnto it ſelfe the ordering of religion, if the parliament may not? When you ſay then, that you may not deale in the matters of religion, becauſe the determinations of that cauſe is referred vnto the Biſhops aſſembled in the conuocation houſe, who in their Cannons, are to prouide and ſee that the church be not in a decaied ſtate, do you not thereby thinke you rob your ſelues of your owne prerogatiue and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and take order that the church without controuerſie may be ſtarued and ſpoiled.</p>
            <p>In deed if the conuocation houſe were ſuch as it ought to be, vz. a ſinod of ſincere, and godly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned miniſters, wherein matters of relligion were determined of according to the worde, and the cauſe of God heard with out partiallitie, then in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deed were it their partes to ſet downe for the direction of the parliament, ſuch thinges as were behoofull for the glorie of God, and the good of his church, &amp; the parliament by their direction according to the word, ought to enjoine all the miniſters and people, whatſoeuer ſhould be thus <pb n="46" facs="tcp:14778:31"/> enacted by the ciuil ſtate. And if the conuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion houſe were ſuch an aſſembly, then were it not laweful for the parliament, to eſtabliſh any thing in the matters apertaininge vnto the pure worſhip of God, among their people, but that wherein they ſhoulde be directed, by the aduiſe of the churche gouernours. For as in a chriſtian common wealth, where the ciuill ſtate ſincerely fauoureth the true worſhip of the Lord, it is not tollerable, no not for the right and lawful, much<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe (ſay the vſurping tiranical gouernors of the church) eſtabliſh any thing in the church, but by the authoritie of the chriſtian magiſtrat: ſo wher there are godly wiſe and ſincere miniſters, it is vnlawfull for the ciuill gouernour, to order any thing in the church within his domminions, but by their direction according to the word. So that I doe not denie, but that the conuocation houſe being an aſſembly of true and lawful church of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, you ought to vſe their adviſe and direction how the wants of the church might be ſupplied. But you ſhoulde not permit them to enact what they would by their owne authoritie, eſpecially their decrees being as now they are, to the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of corruptions, and to the continuance of vngodly callings within theſe dominions. And if you mean to giue ouer your right in dealing with the caſe of God vnto the conuocation houſe, to what end ſhall the ſtates of the land meete toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in parliament, be euer againe ſued vnto.</p>
            <p>But alaſſe, that any thing in church cauſes, ſhalbe referred vnto that aſſemblie, which would not ſtand as it doth, if there weare that good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the church which the Lord requireth, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14778:31"/> and as long as it doeth ſtand, muſt needs be the cauſe of all diſorders therein, and muſt needs be a meanes of continuing that ſtaruing ignoranuce which raigneth in this land. Why my Lords, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the cauſe of religion vnto the Conuocation houſe, is nothing els, but to charge the wolues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of the diſpleaſure of careful ſhepherds, to ſee that the lambes may be fedd, beſides the injurious derogation that thereby is offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the liberties of this houſe.</p>
            <p>And that it may appear how juſtly I apeal from that ſinagogue, vnto this high court of parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and what ſmall hope there is to be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of reforming the abuſes of our Church, if the redreſſe be committed vnto that meeting; you of the honorable court of parliament are to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the conuocation houſe condemneth this cauſe of chriſt now in hand, before it be hard: and that their onely endeuours who are there mett, is howe to preuent him from bearing rule in the Church by his owne lawes. For it is well knowne, that all of them haue banded and linked them ſelues together, to maintaine the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Church, whereof I haue before ſpoken; as the vngodly and popiſh hierarchie of biſhops, the ignorant miniſtery, &amp;c. Which thing ſhal be manifeſted by the conſideration of the perſones, who are admitted vnto the conſultation &amp; mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing. And they are of 2. ſorts. Firſt, theſe whoe by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſuperiority they vſurp over their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, muſt needs be the chief doers in that houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow ignorant, vnconſcionable, and vnfit for the gouernment of the Church ſoeuer they be. Of which number, are our Archbb. and L. biſhops,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14778:32"/> &amp;c. The ſecond ſort is of theſe, who hauing no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to be there, in reſpect of anye ſuperioritie they beare in the Churche, are therefore elected and choſen to be there as the clarks of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation houſe, &amp;c. But there is ſuch freedome and liberty in the choyſe of theſe men, that great care and heede is alwayes had by our L. Bb. that none ſhalbe choſen thither, but ſuch, as for good cauſes are knowen to bee vtter enemies vnto all ſinceritie, and ſtrong maintainers of the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed corruptions: if any other by ſome meanes be gotten thither, who doth but once mention the healing of the wounds of our Church, he is ſtraightwaies taken for a Nicodemus among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; namely, for a man fauoring that ſide, which none of the great Scribes and Phariſes can brook, and lightly they take that order with him, which the Iewes tooke with thoſe, who profeſſed our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt; that is, they banniſh him out of their Synagogue. To be briefe, whoſoeuer are of the houſe there is nothing done there, but what the former ſort; to wit, L. archb. &amp; Bb. would haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted. For the reſt, eyther cannot or wil not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their proceedings. The whole ſway then, &amp; direction of this ſynod, being in their hands, who are for the moſt part, the greateſt cauſe of the teares of our Church; will you referre the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of religion, &amp; the reformation of the church vnto the Conuocation houſe? I haue alreadye ſhewed, that you ought to be ſo far from permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto L. Bb. the diſpoſition of any thing beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto the Church of God, as the very names and places ſhould be razed from vnder your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. And wofull experience theſe 30. full <pb n="49" facs="tcp:14778:32"/> yeares, hath taught vs what a lamentable refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation theſe men now bring to paſſe, if they may haue their owne wils. Why theſe men my Lords, and conſequently, the whole Conuocation houſe are in judgement contrarye vnto our<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 22.25.</note> Sauiour Chriſt; for they holde it lawfull for miniſters to be Lordes ouer their brethren. Theſe men my Ll. are of judgement, that the exhortation of the Apoſtle Peter, was not directed vnto them? The Elders which are among you, ſayth the Apoſtle, I beſeech, which am alſo an Elder, and a witnes of the ſufferings of Chriſt, &amp; alſo a pertaker of the glorye that ſhalbe reuealed, Feede the flocke of God which dependeth vppon you, caring for it, not by conſtraint, but willingly, not for filthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſake, but of a readie minde, not as though ye were Lords ouer Gods heritage, but that ye may be enſamples to the flocke; and when the chiefe ſhepheard ſhall appeare, you ſhall receiue an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible crowne of glory. Theſe men I ſay, are in judgement, contrary vnto this bleſſed Apoſtle, for they drinke it lawful for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be Lords ouer Gods heritage. They are of judgment, that chriſt Ieſus was not ſo faythfull as Moſes, in the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his owne houſe. And do you then thinke that they care how vnfaythfull rhey doe behaue themſelues, in the ouerſight of the Church? They hold the gouernment of the Church to be an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ordinaunce, and ſo holde the Pope to haue ſufficient warrant of his hierarchie. They my Ll. hold the kingdome of Chriſte in the outward go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, to be a kingdome, the lawes whereof, may be chaunged and abrogated, at the pleaſure of man. They do not ſtick to affirme it lawful for <pb n="50" facs="tcp:14778:33"/> them, to teach many thinges, not included in the commiſſion giuen by our ſauiour Chriſt vnto his Apoſtles. Theſe men reject as vntrue, that which the ſpirite of God hath ſet downe by the Apoſtle Paule, 1. Cor.
1.21. Rom. 10.14. which is, that men are ordinarilye ſaued, by the preaching of the word. For they are perſwaded, that ſaluation may be ordinarily attayned vnto by reading; &amp; ſo they are perſwaded, that the Lorde hath promiſed his ſpirit to ſeale that doctrin in the hearts<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13.</note> of men, which through preaching was neuer made kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto them. What care then will they haue, to ſee the people prouided for of preching, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they are not perſwaded of the ordinary neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie thereof. They my Ll. maintaine the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the dumb and ignorant miniſtery, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our Church hath long ſince gotten her bane. Their judgement is, that they may be tollerated for lawful miniſters, in a chriſtian commonwelth and that the parliament may ſecurely maintain them in our Churche, without all feare of Gods judgementes for tollerating them! O the great hand of God in punniſhing our ingratitude, that in this cleare light of the goſpell, they who take vpon them to be Archſeers, willingly ſee not, that none can be lawfull embaſſadors of Ieſus Chriſt, but they out of whoſe mouthes, this embaſſage is heard;<note place="margin">1. Cor.
5.</note> 
               <hi>VVe beſeech you in Chriſts ſteed, that you be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vnto God:</hi> And yet ſuch is the blindnes of the convocation houſe, that they cannot ſee this.</p>
            <p>But I bluſh to thinke, that they dare once pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to giue any countenance vnto nonreſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that gaſtly and fearfull ſinne: and yet behold notwithſtanding, they are not onely all of them
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14778:33"/> guiltie thereof themſelues, but euen in the books which they haue publiſhed vnto the world, in the defence of their corruptions, they haue not bene aſhamed to advouch the lawfulnes of this vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and deſperat murther: Yea the verye pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits haue rung again &amp; againe, with invectiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt al thoſe that withſtood this their madnes. O my Ll. &amp; you the reſt of the R. honourable and worſhipful of this high court of parliament, I can not ſtay my ſelfe, but I muſt needes in this place, crie vnto you for helpe and juſtice, againſt theſe vnnaturall men. The Conuocation houſe my Ll. defendeth nonreſidencie to be lawfull! Nonre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidencie my Ll. is defended to bee lawfull in the Conuocation houſe! And will you then truſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ouerſight of the people, who are of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they may lawfully ſtarue &amp; murther them? Can you hope for any good to come vnto the church of God from that councel, where it is enacted, that it may be lawfull for a bond of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering nonreſidents to deſtroy the ſame If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the parliament of Englande, there be any care of the glorye of God, and the libertie of his Church; if any pitie and compaſſion of the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſoules of men, let others bee truſted to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide foode for your people, and not thoſe, whoſe very judgements are ſo darkened, that they hold it allowable by the worde, for them to take order, that men may not be fedd. It is now meet my Ll. that they who holde it lawfull for men to make a trade of murther, ſhould be allowed for phiſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And what els are they, who defende the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of nonreſidencie, but ſuche as profeſſe it lawfull for men to bee maintayned (rather then
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14778:34"/> they ſhoulde want liuing) euen by the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their brethren.</p>
            <p>Is it not great pitie then, but that this Conuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation houſe ſhould be ſtil countenanced by the ſtate, to be the only place whence reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all the things out of order in our Church ſhould be expected? For therein doubtles, any thing ſhal be heard, which may tende to the furtherance of the goſpell; ſeeing none ſound (few excepted) are admitted into that aſſembly, who are not guiltie of the merciles and cruell murther of ſoules, as beeing all of them for the moſt part, curſed and bloody nonreſidents. And is it not great pitie, but that the parliament ſhould ſtaye and go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the reformation of religion, then it ſhould bee directed by the Conuocation houſe. For it may be hoped, out of queſtion, that the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion houſe will ſee, that no calling be henceforth tollerated in the miniſterie, but ſuch as the Lord in his worde warranteth to be lawfull. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may bee hoped, that the leaders thereof will not ſticke to put downe Archbiſhops, and L. Bb. that Chriſt alone, by the officers which he in his word hath appointed may rule in his church. They will not abide that anye blemiſhed &amp; may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Leuit ſhould come neere to the Lords San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, nor any phariſaicall high prieſt ſhoulde vſurpe anye authoritie ouer his brethren in this lande. If this hope might be conceiued of them, then in deed woulde they bee meete to cure the diſeaſes of our church. But the truth is, that there is no reaſon why this ſhould be expected at their hands, becauſe they are ſo far (as this whole land knoweth) from hauing anye remorſe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull <pb n="53" facs="tcp:14778:34"/> and vngodly callings wherein they nowe remaine, that their practiſes againſt God and his trueth, doe proclaime vnto the worlde, that they neuer meane to reſtore againe her owne autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie vnto the Churche, whereof by their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips it hath bene ſpoyled.</p>
            <p>I haue determined with my ſelfe, not to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble this honorable aſſemblie at this time, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny large diſcourſe, concerning theſe men &amp; their dealngs: otherwiſe, I would ſhew by euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t profs, that they (and ſo the whole Conuocation houſe) are guiltie of ſuch crimes, as the fauorableſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of their proceedings, woulde of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie be drawne to giue this ſentence againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, namely; That they are intollerable oppugners of Gods glory, and vtter enemies vnto the liberties of his Church. And they ſhould alſo be drawne to confeſſe, that the parliament in maintayning the Conuocation houſe, did maintayne and defend, together with the hindering and ſmoothering of the trueth, not only the deformed ruines; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the lamentable oppreſſion of the Church. So that it ſhould appeare, that as long as that houſe ſtandeth, as at this day it doth; there could be no hope at all, that either Gods heauenly trueth ſhould haue free paſſage, or the Churche her ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie in this kingdome. The briefe heades of the publike crimes, whereof the leaders of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation houſe are guiltie, I will here ſet downe, &amp; they ſhalbe herafter evidently prooued, if they vnto whoſe charge they are laid dare deny them</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, their very callings and places, that is, the callings &amp; places of our Archbiſhops and L. Bb. are ſuch as they they cannot poſſibly, <pb n="55" facs="tcp:14778:35"/> but diſhonour God, and bereaue the Church of her libertie by continuing in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Secondly their practiſes in thoſe places, for the maintenaunce of their tyrannicall ſuperioritie, &amp; others the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Church, which they wilfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto all trueth and aequitie doe maintaine, are ſuch, as by them, they haue not onely mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly maymed the outward face of the church, in the matter of gouernement and ceremonies: but alſo grieuouſly wounded the ſame, in the matters of doctrine and ſacramentes: vnto the mayntenance of all which corruptions in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Churche, in the ceremonies, in the doctrin &amp; ſacraments, they haue joyned the crimes of ſeducing and deceiuing the ciuill ſtate and people, by bearing all eſtates in hand, that al hath bene and is well in the Church; and in like manner, as much as in them lay, they haue vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and perſecuted as many of the deare ſeruants of God, as haue but entended to motion the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of any of the former corruptions. Hereof if I ſhall not be able to prooue the eyes and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of this ſynagogue, &amp; conſequently the whol houſe to bee guiltie; let mee to the terror of all ſlaunderers, be put to all the torments that may bee invented. The Conuocation houſe cannot here object, that I deal injuriouſly with the whol aſſembly, by laying vnto the charge of the whol, thoſe crimes whereof our Bb. alone are guiltie. For the whole houſe, neuer as yet, diſauowed the hierarchie of Bb. their practiſes in vrging ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, in maintayning the dumbe miniſterie, nonreſidencie, &amp;c. And vntill the corruptions of the Bb. be ouerthrown in that aſſembly, the whol <pb n="55" facs="tcp:14778:35"/> houſe ſhall be ſtill juſtly ſubject vnto the former accuſations.</p>
            <p>See now my Lords whether they doe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray their impietie who think, that men weary them ſelues about ſmall matters, when they call for a reformation of the church. And ſee whether there be not many and vrgent cauſes, to inforce the parliament to take the gouernment of the Church out of the hands of theſe men, vnleſſe the continuance of the ruinous breaches of our Church would be ſtil maintined, it is not the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of capp, ſurplice, tippet, and other beggerlie and popiſh ceremonies, whence al the diſſention and diſſagreement in our church is ſprong vp. But the controuerſies ariſe, becauſe our Archbb. and Bb. are not permitted with the ſilence and conſent of the ſeruants of God, to ſmother, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, depraue &amp; corrupt, the truth of that true religion which in name they profeſſe, &amp; to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and captiuate the church of God in this land. Thoſe who withſtand, their vngodly proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, haue hitherto dutifully kept them ſelues within the bonds of the calings, wherin the Lord hath placed them, they haue in al ſubmiſſion and duty entreated that the cauſe of God might be equally hard, and that her Maieſtie and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament would amend the things proued to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, they haue neuer as yet, preſumed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, to take in hand the correction of any thing. But how quietly on the other ſide, haue the leaders of the conuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> houſe behaued them ſelues, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a redres hath bin caled for at the hands of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil ſtate? Surely they haue alwais hitherto preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, to impriſonments and bonds <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14778:36"/> and would neuer ſuffer the truth to haue the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, nor any man with quietnes to ſtand in the defence therof. And therefore alſo, al the tumults that hereafer are like to ariſe in the Church of God within this land, about theſe controuerſies, the leders of the conuocation houſe, are the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thereof, for they wil not yeeld vnto the truth, but labour by all meanes poſſible, to ſmother the ſame. Gods ſeruants cannot winke at their proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, vnleſſe they would betray Gods truth, and the libertie of his church. The leaſt parte of the ſinnes of our Bb. hath bin in the maintenance of vnprofitable, ſuperſticious, and corrupt cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. If they would but yeeld free paſſage vnto the truth, and hir authority vnto the church in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters, they ſhould not be gretly moleſted for theſe things. And woe be vnto them, if they had rather prouoke god and his church to battel againſt them for the defence of the truth, then receiue the light, &amp; grant peace vnto the church. Concerning her Maieſtie, who (as it is thought) can neuer be induced to aulter the eſtabliſhed gouernment, I anſwere, that if it be made known vnto her, and proued out of the word, that the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed regiment of the church, is traiterous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Maieſtie of Ieſus Chriſt, that it confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the popes ſupremacie. O therfore it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous vnto her crown, that it is beſides the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion giuen by our Sauiour Chriſt vnto his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; and therefore accurſed, that it ſheweth them to be void of all care of re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igion, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly countenance the ſame, and that it calleth for the judgments of God againſt her, and her kingdom, and then if ſhee yeeld not vnto the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing <pb n="57" facs="tcp:14778:36"/> of all ſinful callings, out of the church, I will not deſire to liue, if this be thought a matter wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of death, for a man to be dutyfully perſwaded of his ſoueraigne. Be it that her Maieſtie hath bin moued, by ſome of this houſe, for the redreſſe of the church, you ſhould moue her againe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and neuer leaue vntil you be heard. Great matters are neuer brought to paſſe, without great and mighty endeuours. Our ſinnes haue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſerued, then, that the Lord ſhould at the firſt encline mercy vnto vs, in the ſight of her highnes. Would any of you alter any part of the gouernment of his family, being perſwaded by leud flatterers, that all were well, vnleſſe the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe were ſhewed, and you earneſtly dealt with for a reformation. And can you then maruel, that our ſoueraigne is hardly drawne to reforme the church, whoſe eſtate, in her hearing, is daily ſaid out of the pulpit to be moſt floriſhing, wheras the deformity therof is not made knowne vnto her. I know it is no ſmal perſwaſion that ſhould driue a monarch, to abrogat the receued conſtitutions, and eſtabliſh new, vnles the vnanſwerable neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiry thereof, were made knowne vnto her or him. I am perſwaded that her Maieſtie knoweth not, the exacting neceſſitie, that lieth vppon her ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of reforming the church. Shee knoweth not the eſtate of her vntaught and damned ſubiects to be as it is. Wherefore ſerue parliament men, if her eies muſt be in al places to ſee euery thing, and what doe you ſee, if you do not ſee our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and lament it? I grant indeed, that of this point ſhe ought to be moſt careful, but if of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, the waightieſt matters be omitted, ſhoulde <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14778:37"/> not you put her in mind hereof? And in ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on entreat her and neuer leaue entreating, vntill ſhee yeeld to turne away the wrath of God from her, and her kingdome, by abolliſhing vngodly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and reſtoring beauty vnto Zion.</p>
            <p>Well, I haue forged, the moſt notable ſlanders that euer were coined, or els, the ſtate of my cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey vnder her Maieſties gouernment, is very mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, &amp; yours no leſſe lamentable, if it ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue. And if you make not the ſame knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Maieſtie, and ſee it be ſpeedely amended, the Lord make Quene Elizabeth, and her crown free, from the bloude of her deſtroyed people. And I pray God if it be his will, that their ſoules be not required at your hands in the day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in quick and dead ſhalbe judged.</p>
            <p>But it may be, that you wil pretend the wante to be ſo difficult, that it cannot poſſiblie be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Do what lieth in you, and then the Lord is anſwered. The farther you go herein, the eſier wilbe the paſſage, you are deſired no more, then not to countenance ſinn, and for reformation to go no farther then meanes will reach. Becauſe it is a worke of difficultie, therefore muſt you needs hinder the ſame by lawe as you doe, by tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerating theſe abuſes; Becauſe the whol worke is difficult, therefore ſhal it not begin; Becauſe it is a hard matter to plant the ordinance of God, therefore muſt the breache thereof be in force, &amp; maintained? Becauſe in Canaan the ſonnes of Anak,<note place="margin">Num. 13.14.</note> &amp; towns walled vp to heauen (mountains of pretenſed excuſes, haue ben ſeene) therefore muſt you needs ſuffer the people, brought by her Maieſtie and you, out of Egipt, to remaine ſtil in <pb n="59" facs="tcp:14778:37"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he wildetnes, on this ſide Iordan, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder theſe men, the dumb miniſters L. Bb. I meane which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it for nothing els, then to be leaders, whenſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>portunitie ſhall ſerue,<note place="margin">Num. 14.4.</note> to bring the people again <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto Egipt? Becauſe our land, by reaſon of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in ſinn, and that wee haue not had ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful workmen among vs, doth not now bring forth religion and godlineſſe in the meaſure it ſhould, therefore muſt you needs be ſure, that profaneſſe and atheiſme ſhalbe ſowen, and the breach of Gods lawe flouriſh there, in the perſons of thoſe men? Therefore the juſt Lord,<note place="margin">Ezek. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> wil be juſt in the midſt of you, whenſoeuer he reckoneth for theſe things, becauſe you are ſo far from doing what you may in the planting of godlineſſe, that you ſuffer impietie againſt his Maieſtie, to bear ſway, and that by law and authority.</p>
            <p>Concerning the hardneſſe of the work, this I make knowne vnto you, that if you wilbe ruled by the cannon of the word, you ſhalbe able with eaſe and the good liking of your people, to do ſo much therein, as you ſhal deliuer your owne liues from the wrath of God. But if that rule ſhal take place no farther, then it may ſtand with the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Lord Biſhops, and other corruptions of the eccleſiaſticall ſtate, I ſee not what you can ſay vnto the Lord, when he hath made you an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment, and an hiſſing vnto all the nations vnder heauen:<note place="margin">Nehe. 9.39</note> but ſurely thou art juſt in all that is come vpon vs for wee would not be ruled by thy words.</p>
            <p>Wel the word teacheth and requireth of you 2. things and no more, in this worke. In both it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth your practiſe, if you would be directed by <pb n="60" facs="tcp:14778:38"/> it. Firſt it requireth, that Wales may be redreſſe by proclaiming that commiſſion giuen by ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sauiour Chriſt vnto his apoſtles, Math. 28.19.20 in euery corner thereof, and both the parts of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commiſſion, it requireth to be kept inuiolably as well that, of goe preach and baptiſe, as the o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, of teach them to obſerue, whatſoeuer I haue commanded you. Secondly, while you ſtay the Lords leaſure to raiſe vp fit men for this worke in euery congregation, it requireth, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple where preachers cannot be placed at the firſt, may haue ſom ſtay, that inconueniences be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For the Lord will not haue religion, ſo vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly eſtabliſhed, as that the inconueniences that might growe thereby vnto the ciuil ſtate, as much as may be, be not wiſely preuented; in the effectinge hereof, 2. things are to be looked vnto, both of them greatlie furthering the worke. Firſt the bleſſing of God is to be labored for, by humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling your ſelues and your people with Daniel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.1.3.</note> in faſting and praier, and then you ſhal ſee, he wilbe with your endeuours. Secondly you muſt enjoine euery one according vnto his place, to haue a hand in this worke, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the gentlemen, &amp; people that ſhalbe found forward, by gracing and countenancing them for their forwardneſſe in religion, and ſhewing that the more forward they be, the more credit they are like to purchaſe with your Hh. And you muſt not ſuffer an vncircumciſed mouth,<note place="margin">Nom. 14.39.</note> to bring a ſlander vpon that good land, whereunto the Lord offereth to bring you and your people,<note place="margin">Nom. 14.10.</note> if you would obey, much leſſe, to lift vp a ſtonn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Caleb or Ioſhuah, that withſtand the fury
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14778:38"/> of a whol wicked hoaſt in the defence of the Lord. For otherwiſe, if you ſuffer al to ſit ſtil, and looke vppon our deſolations, the moſt to liue on the ſweetnes of our ruines, and diſcountenance all that labour therein, you can looke for nothing elſe ſhortly; but that lamentable complaint, and it is a great work of God, that we haue heard the ſame long agoe, of euerie poſſeſſor in this land. Whyther ſhall wee goe? Our brethren and their hard intertainment haue diſcouraged our harts;<note place="margin">Deut. 1.18.</note> woulde to God that we had died in the Land of Egipt, would to God we weare dead: were it not better for vs to turne into Egipt?<note place="margin">Nom. 14.2.</note> com let vs make a captaine and returne thyther. The land indeed is a good land, whereunto, when our ſoueraigne brought vs out of Egipt, wee entended to make our iorney: but alaſſe, we are neuer able to ſtand againſt the pouertie, loſſes, impriſonment, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance by our ſuperiors, that our brethren haue ſuſtained, which haue ſet their faces againſt this land, neuer able to ſwallowe vp the ſlanders and bitter names of Puritans, preciſians, traitos, ſeditious libellers, &amp;c. that wee ſee, raiſed againſt thoſe that would bring vs thyther. And therefore my Ll. and the reſt of the high aſſemblie, in vaine ſhall you vſe other meanes, and leaue this vnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted</p>
            <p>The redreſſe of Wales, conſiſteth of 2. partes, both muſt be ſpeedely ſet vpon by your Hh. or els certainly the judgements of God will finde you out. Firſt you muſt aboliſhe out of the Churche, whatſoeuer you ſhal finde to be a breach of gods ordinance (as I haue prooued dumbe miniſters, nonreſidents, and L. Bb. to be) or els your refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation <pb n="62" facs="tcp:14778:39"/> will be little better then that of the<note n="a" place="margin">Kin.
17.33.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritanes, who feared Iehouah, but worſhipped their owne gods. I woulde haue it marked in this place, what is required at the handes of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that it may thereby appeare, whether with any colour of reaſon, this part of the petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in hand can be denied. The parliament is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to enact, that no vnlawfull calling be tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated vnder the gouernment within the church of God in Wales; if they will not yeeld vnto this part of the ſuite, now put vp in the behalfe of that people; what cloake doe they leaue vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, whereby they may but couer their ſmall care to glorifie God? Is not the caſe to be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied at, that an aſſembly profeſſing true religion, cannot be drawne to yeeld vnto ſo juſt a requeſt, it is a hard matter I grant, to build the church of God: Men moſt willing to bring that worke to paſſe, cannot doe it; but there is no difficultie in the worlde, for the parliament of England to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that, although they cannot go ſo far in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the Goſpell as they would wiſhe; yet that they will not at any hand maintaine by lawe any thing, which may hinder the courſe thereof. Wel let as manye as are parliament men, looke vnto this, as ſure as the Lord liueth, they ſhall anſwere one day, before him, who is the judge of quicke and dead, and giue a reaſon why they would not conſent to root out ſinne, and the breach of gods law, out of this common wealth. Do they ſeek the innovation of the ſtate, who deſire, that no lawe or ſtatute may be in force, which vpholdeth the tranſgreſſing of Gods holy inſtitution? Or may they be accounted dangerous ſubjects vnto their <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14778:39"/> prince, who cannot abide that any treſon againſt God ſhould be countenanced? Well, this branche of the ſuite is ſuch, as the Tridentine conſpiracie would bluſh to profes the rejecting therof. What then may be thought of the high court of parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if it cannot be there granted?</p>
            <p>The ſecond meanes for you to redreſſe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Wales muſt bee this; you muſt place as many godly learned men as can be found, to call the people, and ſee them prouided for. But here great aduice is to be taken, where, and howe they be placed. Firſt then, you are to looke out the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that are fitteſt by all likelihood to receiue the word, and vnto thoſe, to haue the ſpecialleſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. For ſeeing you are not able at once, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the whole countrie with able men; you muſt firſt haue regard of that part of the haruiſt, which is moſt readie for the mowers. This reſpect we ſee the ſpirite of God to haue had, Act. 16.7. Where the ſpirit woulde not ſuffer Paule to go to Bythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, but rather tooke his iourney to Macedonia, where by reuelation, verſe 9.10. hee was aſſured, that there was preparation made for the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the goſpell. Concerning the other point, the miniſters that ſhalbe ſent, muſt not be ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red aſunder, one here, and another there in the countrie; neither ſent one by one, but many muſt be ſent together, &amp; placed ſo nere one another, as may be. And ſo the miniſters hauing aedification, and comfort one by another, ſhall neither decay in their gifts, nor be diſcouraged; and the people by this meanes, ſhalbe ſure to be thorowly called. If the complaint be made for want of ſufficient men, and ſufficient ſtay for their liuings: For the <pb n="64" facs="tcp:14778:40"/> men, take al thoſe, whome the Lorde hath made fit for this worke, and he can require no more at your hands, vntill he rayſe vp more: which if he neuer do, your good endeuours, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto ſtudents and others, not being wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to bring this to paſſe, he cannot in juſtice pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you, though your people be not taught. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you haue ſene all thoſe well beſtowed, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he quallified for the calling, and ſo doe now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a bleſſing from him vpon your labours, that you might ſend more. The ſubterfuge will be but the coat of a net, to aske (as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly your prelats do) how there ſhould be poſſibly founde, as many learned men, as wales requireth, ſeeing they who are found, are not placed there. And do you deale well with the Lorde, that becauſe all cannot be brought at once to ſerue him, as he willeth, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that may ſhall not? The ſame is to bee ſayd of the miniſters liuings. Remoue the dumb miniſters, nonreſidents, L. Bb. (if you will not do this, you go beſides the word of God, and ſo there is no direction for you) and there will be more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings void, able to maintain godly miniſters, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe I fear me, good men found to ſupply their places. And verely I maruail, what men perſwade themſelues the Lord to be; whereas they thinke, he can be ſatisfied with ſuch ſielie ſhifts? Is it not a ſtrange matter to find Church liuings in wales for L. Bb. nonreſidents, and dumbe miniſters, to ſinne againſt God, and ſtarue ſoules withall, and deny any to be there, for godly miniſters to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God, and worke the ſaluation of his people. The children muſt ſtarue for want of bread, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the dogs before their eies muſt be fed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14778:40"/> Good reaſon? yea, but the remouing of thoſe men, would be likely to ſet the land on fire. Marke how ſubtill the deuill is, in the maintenaunce of his kingdome. When godly miniſters are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe they will not linke themſelues with wicked Bb. to betray the kingdome of Chriſte, &amp; ouerthrow the lawes of this land, there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience feared. But if Satans meſſengers be once ſhoued at, behold, the land will not be able to bear this loſſe. I grant indeed, that men which make no conſcience for gaine ſake, to breake the law of the aeternall, and maſſaker ſoules (as theſe do) are dangerous ſubjects, and not to be truſted any farther then they are fed.</p>
            <p>The moſt of them are vnſauerye ſalte, ſuch as haue hitherto liued vpon ſacriledge and the ſpoil of ſoules. Order might be taken, notwithſtanding by the magiſtrate, that theſe and their families, ſhould neyther want thinges neceſſarie for their outwarde eſtate: nor yet be maintayned in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. For the people, the ſtay for them is, eyther in regarde of publike meetings on the Sabboth, or the ſacraments, mariage or buriall. For the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Sabboth, the worde requireth they ſhould, if poſſiblie they can, reſort where prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching is, vntill good miniſters be placed in euery pariſh: if the places be far, as commonly our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes be verye large, and it is not likely in ſhort time, to plant preachers ſo neere together, as the people may euery Saboth reſort vnto them, they muſt be enjoyned to meete together in their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh churches, &amp; ſome diſcreet man among them ſelues to read the worde, and vſe ſome forme of prayers, as ſhalbe thought meeteſt: by the aduiſe <pb n="66" facs="tcp:14778:41"/> of the godly learned. Concerning the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the word requireth, they ſhould reſort vnto a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching miniſter for them, and not attempt to keep their children vnbaptized any longer, then they muſt of neceſſitie. Mariage is moſt conveniently to be don by the miniſter, but is no proper eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall worke of the miniſter; and therefore may be ſolemnized by others, at the magiſtrats appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Concerning burial, it is a worke of chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an charitie, and being the laſt duetie that we are to performe towards the departed; we ought to accompany them decently and orderly, with all comlines to the graue. The word mentioneth or includeth noe forme of prayer vſed at buriall; therefore they are ſuperfluous, neyther is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter as in an action belonging to his office, to haue any more to doe herein, then any other of the brethren.</p>
            <p>Thus I haue ſet downe vnto your Hh. the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly courſe in regarde of ſubſtance, that the worde warranteth to be taken in ſuch a deformed eſtate as ours is. And nowe my Ll. and the reſt of this honorable aſſembly, let my counſell be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto you, breake of your ſinnes, by rooting out theſe plants, which the Lorde neuer planted in his vineyarde, and your iniquities, by abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame, ſo much as in you lieth; ſo there may be a healing of your former ouerſight. If not the Lords face will be againſt you, yours, and the wholland for euil, &amp; not for good. Oh my Lords, is it not a miſerable caſe, that men ſhould ſo liue vnder your gouerment in this life, as they cannot poſſibly, but liue in hel in the life to come. Oh my Ll. heauen cannot be obtayned whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are gon.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14778:41"/> Oh my Ll. now is the time for the goſpell to flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in Wales or neuer. Oh my Ll. if her Maieſtie and your honors (whome from my verye heart I wiſh the Lorde to bleſſe) ſhould be gone the way of all the world; for mine owne part, the ſtaffe of mine hope, to ſee any good done amongſt my brethren ſhould be broken. Blame me not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if I deale earneſtly in a cauſe of ſo great a moment, and ſo vnlikely to be obtayned of our wofull poſterities, whom my ſuit in a moſt neere ſort concerneth. Oh, why ſhould they haue cauſe to ſay, the Lord be judge between vs and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours which were vnder Queene Elizabeth, in the dayes of our fathers; for they might haue opened our eyes, and healed our woundes, which now alaſſe, are deſperat and paſt recouery.</p>
            <p>It is now full 30. yeares and vpward, ſince Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon hath bin ouerthrowne in Wales, rather by the voice of her maieſties good laws (whom good Lord forget not for this worke) then the ſounde of any trumpet, from the mouthes of the ſonnes of Aaron among vs. But alaſſe, what ſhall we and our poſterities be the better for this, if Sion bee not built. And what comfort can Zerubbabel, or Nehemiah haue, to bring them out of Babylon, if they meane but to reaedifie Shilo, ſeeing it is the beautie of Sion, wherein the Lorde delighteth. We haue cauſe in deed to thanke God, that this wicked citie hath beene by her Maieſtie broken downe in ſome ſort; but are neuer the better, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the walles of Sion lie euen with the grounde. Nowe for the ſpace of 28. yeares, no man greatly laboured to her Majeſtie, the parliament, or the people themſelues, eyther by ſpeaking or writing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14778:42"/> in the behalfe of eyther of theſe vnreconcilable cities. Men belike, thinking no more to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at their hands, then the razing of Babel, and the diuel as yet, contenting himſelfe with Bethel. The laſt parliament, by al liklihod the very ſame week vpon a ſodaine, the interpriſes of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of both in 2. ſeueral books, iſſuing from
2. of the remoteſt corners in our lands. (Southwales and Northwales) was taken in hand. The one of the books pleading the cauſe of Sion, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minig forth by publike authority and alowance, was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected vnto her Maieſtie and the parliament, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring at their hands by vertue of the lords own mandatory letters, the performance of this work ſhewing by euidence of greateſt antiquitye, this to be required of duty at their hands, as a part of the homadge, due vnto his highnes, whoſe foeda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and vaſſales, all the princes and ſtates vnder heauen muſt acknowledg themſelues to be, and a portion of that inheritance being theirs by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall diſſent, from their predeceſſors, the godly kings and rulers, who time out of minde alwaies laid their ſhoulders vnto this burthen.<note place="margin">y druch Chriſtiano-gawl.</note> The other written in weltch, printed in an obſcure caue in Northwales publiſhed by an author vnknowne &amp; more vnlerned (for I think he had neuer read any thing but the common publiſhed reſolution of. R. P. a booke contayning many ſubſtantiall errors, Fryer Ruſh, and other ſhamful fables) ſtood to by non, and hauing no reaſon to ſhew why his Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon ſhould be raedefied, it contained it ſelf within the hands of a fewe priuate men, and neuer durſt to this houre be made knowne vnto any of our mageſtrats. Both the books in this thing had the <pb n="69" facs="tcp:14778:42"/> ſame ſucceſſe, in that both together they fel into the hands of the prelats, who as they pretend, are enemies vnto both places, but vndoubtedly vnto Sion eſpecially, as it apeared by their hard dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the patrone of that cauſe,<note place="margin">This is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</note> whereas the fautors of the other, being alſo in their handes, were either not at al delt with, or very curteouſly entertained of them. The reaſon of their enemity vnto both, but their hatred vnto Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, that neuer I feare me, meaning to go thether, and conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by lawe to be enemies vnto the other, they haue of the gold of Caldea, and the droſſe of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem compacted them a citty, wherewith they meane to content them ſelues vntil they returne to Babel again, or (the Lord be merciful vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) vnto a worſe place. Haue they not therfore good cauſe to be the more beholding to the on for the gold, then the other for the droſſe; Wel be you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hereof, that they who ſtirred vp both theſe inſtruments, both at one time, will neuer ſuffer them to ceaſe, vntil in Wales either a church of Chriſt, or a ſinagogue of ſathan be built. Out of queſtion the concurring of both cauſes, ſheweth that the lord hath ſom ſecret work in the matter. Sathans inſtruments for their parts, were neuer buſier then they are at this houre, and ſhal I be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent? They trecherouſly againſt the lawes of God and this land ſeek to bring the people again vnto Egipt. I according vnto both, endeuour neuer to let them reſt, vntil it pleaſe the Lord by meanes of her Maieſty, and the parlament, to bring them within the land of promiſe, no though they were vppon mount Nebo, whence with their eies they might view the ſame. They haue delt, and deal ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14778:43"/> with poor ſoules in dark corners, and dare not make knowne the fabulous cauſe. I haue delt al this while in the face of the ſun, and nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtate of the land aſſembled together. I-want not a good cauſe, and by the grace of god, it ſhal neuer want the poore defence which I cann yeld vnto it, or hide the face as long as I liue; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you countenance it or no, I know that on day it ſhal preuail, when this wilbe the Lord knoweth beſt: but the matter is, whether you wil embrace Chriſt in the building of his Church, or Sathan in continuing the breaches thereof. Therfore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine this cauſe, &amp; you giue Sathan the foile, reject this, and you ſtrengthen him. And try if you deny it the hearing, whether the very papiſts in this land, wil not be thereby encoraged to ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate vnto the parliament, that you would graunt them the liberty of their ſeared conſciences, to commit publike idolatry</p>
            <p>Al that hitherto I haue ſpoken, hath ben ſaid ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the cauſe of Chriſt, which is a good cauſe, or in the behalfe of Sathan. If I ſeeke the building of his ſinagog, wil you let me liue? If of the church of Chriſt, wil you deny me your help? which yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe, in the name of the eternal God I require, &amp; for the precious deth &amp; paſſions ſake of Ieſus Chriſt, I earneſtly deſire at your handes. My Ll. and whoſoeuer are parlament men, as you would haue the Lord to entertaine your ſouls in the life to come, as you would haue him ſhewe you any mercy, as you loue her Maieſty and her life, as you would haue the continuance of her peaceable raign over vs, which the Lord vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly threatneth to ſhorten, becauſe he woulde <pb n="71" facs="tcp:14778:43"/> bring deſtruction vpon you and vs al, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his truth, as you would not haue your names razed from vnder heauen, as you would not haue the Lord to bring vpon vs and our land, the Spaniſh, Italian, Romiſh or Guiſian forces, as you would not haue theſe, who ſhal liue to ſee the deſolation and deſperat ſorrow, which the Lord is likely to bring vpon this land, not abide to ſee you or your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ride, or go in the ſtrets, as you would not haue the moſt contemtible to ſtretch forth his hand vpon the dereſt things you poſſes, and offer violence vnto the frute of your bodies? So entertaine this cauſe, grant this ſuite, and be careful of the Lords true ſeruice in wales. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the vengeance of God I feare me, will neuer leaue you and your poſterities, as long as there is a man of your houſes left vnder heauen.</p>
            <p>Ezekiel in deed is not nowe liuing, to put you in mind of the neceſſity of redreſſing the things amis, by laying open the corruptions of all eſtates vnder your gouernment, as he doth cap. 22. of his propheſie. His words I wil ſet downe that you may wey our eſtate, with the time wherin the prophet liued, and ſee whether the Lorde wil ſpare you &amp; vs, if we ſtil prouoke him to ſmite. There is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of her prophets in the middeſt thereof, ſaith the prophet, like a roring lyon, rauening the pray, they haue deuoured ſoules, they haue taken the riches and the precious thinges: they haue made her many widdows in the middeſt thereof, her prieſts haue broken my law, and haue defiled my holy things: they haue put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the holy &amp; profane, neither diſcerned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the vncleane and the cleane, and haue hid <pb n="72" facs="tcp:14778:44"/> their eies from my ſabboth, and I am profaned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Her princes in the middeſt thereof are like wolues rauening the pray, to ſhed blood and to deſtroy ſoules, for their owne couetous lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre. And her prophets haue daubed her with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered morter, ſeeing vanities, and deuininge lyes vnto them, ſayihg, thus ſaith the Lord Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah, when Iehouah had not ſpoken. The people of the land haue violently oppreſſed, by robbing and ſpoiling, and haue vexed the poor and needy: yea they haue opreſſed the ſtranger againſt right. Thus far Ezechiel. Be the ſinns of our prophets, of our princes, and of our people the ſame, that here he ſpeketh againſt, be they greater or be the leſſe: yet without controuerſie, if the Lord may ſay, I haue ſought for a man in the parliament of England, that ſhould make vp the hedge, &amp; ſtand in the gapp, before me for the land, that I ſhould not deſtroy it, but I found none: then woe be vnto vs, for that ſhal follow, which is ſet downe in the prophete. Therefore haue I powred out mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation vppon them, and conſumed them with the fier of my wrath: their own waies haue I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered vpon their heads, ſaith the Lord Iehouah; And vnleſſe there were juſt cauſe to thinke that this Lorde, had either already or ſhortly ment to pronounce this ſentence againſt vs, we might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne and ſcorn at the broken aſſalts of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, or any other the enemies of the Goſpel, and her Maieſties whoſoeuer. But as long as we giue not the right hand to the Lord, by entering into his ſanctuarye, we haue juſt cauſe to feare a nation that is no nation, much more a people in number as the ſand, which is by the ſeaſhore. Our <pb n="73" facs="tcp:14778:44"/> leagues and moſt ſtable couenants with the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; the Lord will ſoone diſanul, ſtanding thus at the ſtaffes end with his Maieſtie, as we doe.</p>
            <p>Let it not be ſayd in this pIace, that the Lord would not haue ſo wonderfully wrought our late deliueraunce, out of the hand of the Spaniarde, if he ment at al to haue called the land to recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for the great ignorance, and wicked eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall conſtitutions, which are truly ſayd to be maintained therein. For this, both Moſes and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loman,<note place="margin">Deut. 29.18.49.20.</note> note to be the man of all thoſe that ſhall not prolong their dayes, Moſes warneth al ſtates in any caſe to take heed, that there ſhould not be among them, man, woman, family, nor tribe, which ſhould turne his hart away from the Lord God, ſo that when he heareth the wordes of the curſe, he bleſſe him ſelfe in his hart, ſaying, I ſhall haue peace though I walked after the ſtubborne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mine owne hart, thus adding drunkennes vnto thirſt. For ſaith he, the Lord wil not be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto that man: but then the wrath of the Lorde ſhall ſmoke againſt that man, and euery curſe that is written in this booke ſhal light vpon him, and the Lord ſhall put out his name from vnder heauen, &amp; the Lord ſhal ſeperate him vnto euil, according vnto all the curſes that is writen in the booke of the lawe.<note place="margin">Eccleſ.
8.11.13.</note> And Soloman knowing the corruptions of men to be ſuch, as their harts are fully ſet in them to doe euil, becauſe ſentence againſt their euil works is not ſpedely executed, openly teſtifieth, that although a ſinner doe euill an hundreth times, &amp; the Lord prolong his days, yet it ſhal only be well, with them that feare the Lord, and do reuerence before him. But it ſhall <pb n="74" facs="tcp:14778:45"/> not be wel with the wicked (ſaith he) for he ſhalbe like a ſhadow, becauſe he feareth not before God. And therefore although at this time the Lords anger hath not viſited, nor caled the ſinnes of our land to account, with gret extremity by the hand of the Spanyard: yet let vs be aſſured, that it ſhall not goe wel with vs, vnleſſe you of the high court of parliament, ſhew that you feare your God, and doe reuerence before him, in purging out of his holy ſeruice, what ſoeuer is ſuperfluous therein, and in adding whatſoeuer is wanting therevnto. The Lord by that deliuerance, gaue vs warning that he paſſed by vs, but ſo, as vnleſſe the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his ſeruice be clean don away with ſpeed by her Maieſty and the parliament, meaneth to paſſe by vs no more: but to ſuffer his whol diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to fall vppon vs, at his next comming. And in deed, as often as I conſider our late defence from the Spaniſh invaſion, together with our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, I am induced to think, that the Lord then was affected towards vs, as ſomtimes he was to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Iſrael his owne people, concerning whom he ſpeaketh, Deut. 32.26. I haue ſayd, I would ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them abrod, I wold make their remembrance to ceaſe from among men, ſaue that I feared the fury of the enemie, leſt their aduerſaries ſhould wax proud, &amp; leſt they ſhould ſay, our high hand and not the Lord hath done al this. Therefore let not our deliuerance harden, you of the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the ſinn of maintayning the breaches of the Lords houſe. The ſame Lord that wrought our deliuerance, wil ſurely be the cauſe of our ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, if his honor be ſo neglected by you as vſually before time it hath ben. And we are to take heed, <pb n="75" facs="tcp:14778:45"/> leſt the Lord ſeeing our profane, and vaine inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the victory, when we are not a whit bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered thereby, ſend ſome Ieremy among vs which may cry, as he did vnto the king, and ſtates of his time, in the like matter. Thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael, thus ſhal you ſay to the parliament of England. Behold, except at this your meeting, all the deformities that are tollerated in my ſeruice, be at once done a way, and except you grant free paſſage vnto my goſpel: the nauy of the Spaniard which I diſcomfited before you, ſhal come againe, and fight againſt this land, and waſte it with fire and ſword. Therefore deceiue not your ſelues, ſaying, the Spaniardes are ſo weakened by their laſt diſcomfiture, that they are not able to purſue their intended inuaſion, for it ſhal not be ſo. No though you had ſmitten the whole hoſte of the Spaniard, that fought againſt you, and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, but wounded men amonge them: yet ſhould euery man riſe vp in his tent, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run this land. And let vs looke aſſuredly, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the abject and contemtible enemy ſhall aſſaile vs, abject and contemptible I ſay, in al re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes, in compariſon of the value and ſtrength of our men and munition (and the Lord increaſe them a thouſand fold more) that this God, whoſe ſeruice is ſo litle eſtemed of vs, wil ſend a terror into the hart of our valianteſt and ſtouteſt men, ſo that he, whoſe hart is as the hart of a lion, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be as weake as water: and on enemye ſhal chaſe a thouſand of vs, becauſe the hand of the Lord wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be againſt vs for our ſinns. It is not therefore the Spaniſh furniture and preparations: but the ſins within the land, which we are moſt of all to feare.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14778:46"/> For although the army of the Spaniard were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with the arrowes of famine: although the contagious and deuouring peſtilence had eaten them vp by thouſands: although their totterting ſhipps were diſperſed, and caried away with the whirlwinde and tempeſt, although madneſſe and aſtoniſhment were amongſt them, from him that ſitteth in the throane, vnto her that grindeth in the mill: although the Lords reuenging ſword, in the hand of our valiant captaines and ſouldiers, had ſo preuailed againſt them, as it had left none in that vncircumciſed hoaſt, but languiſhing and foyled men, notwithſtanding a contemptible, &amp; wythered remnant, of the plague and famine: a navie of winde and weather beaten ſhips, a refuſe of feeble and diſcomfited men, ſhalbe ſufficiently able to preuaile againſt this lande; vnleſſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe be taken for Gods glory in Wales by your Hh. then hitherto hath bene. If I did ſpeake vnto infidels, &amp; vngodly atheiſts, I know I ſhould not be ſo plaine, becauſe vnto ſuch, the trueth at ſometimes is vnſeaſonably ſpoken. But I ſpeake vnto thoſe, that haue vndertaken the profeſſion of Chriſtianitie, and therefore ſhould at all times be fit to heare the trueth of God. And I know no temporizing trueth, no temporizing judgements of God againſt ſinne; no trueth that is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed vnto chriſtians, becauſe their Hh. cannot brooke the ſame; no trueth that is, eyther not at all, or minſingly to be vttered, becauſe ſtates loue not to here thereof. So that I was in this matter, not to conſider what your high places were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to here, but what was the dutie of your high places to heare. And therefore I ſhould thinke it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14778:46"/> (I proteſt) an vndutifull and flattering petition, to entreat your Hh. not to be offended with mee, for vttering the trueth. As though I ſuppoſed, you would thinke it wonderful, that a man ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to ſpeake, euen in the cauſe of his God, any farther then ſtood with your good liking.</p>
            <p>The ſum of all that the Lord requireth at your hands in the cauſe of his honour, is concluded in theſe 2. points. Firſt, that you abrogate out of the Churche, whatſoeuer you finde therein, to be a breach of Gods ordinaunce. Secondly, that you countenance the preaching of the word, in ſuch ſort, as the courſe thereof be not ſtayed, for the pleaſure or profit of any creature. Theſe poyntes are ſo reaſonable, that whoſoeuer vpon choiſe, &amp; deliberation, denieth any of them (of inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie and want of due examination of matters. I know many things may be done amiſſe) I cannot ſee, what he differeth from a plaine Atheiſt. And therefore againe I admoniſh you, in the name of God, to looke vnto your ſelues, and thorowly to waigh, what the Lorde by the mouth of Ezekiel, threatneth againſt you, if you ſtil refuſe his waies and mainteine theſe bypaths of mans inventions in his Church. You haue feared the ſworde,<note place="margin">Ezek. 11.8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 10.12.</note> ſayth the prophet, and I will bring a ſworde vpon you ſayth the Lord Iehouah, and I will bring you out of the middeſt of this land, and deliuer you into the hands of ſtrangers, and execute judgements among you. You ſhall fall by the ſworde, and you ſhall know that I am the Lorde; for you haue not walked in my ſtatutes, nor executed my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, but haue done after the manner of the heathen that are round about you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:14778:47"/>The lawes offices and officers of our church for the moſt part, being not according to the ſtatuts of the lord, but framed after the maner of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh gouernment, whereby the nations round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs are tiranized by the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſin; that is not a matter to be wondered at, that the alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our eccleſiaſtical ſtate is deſired. And beſides our ſauior Chriſt &amp; his Goſpell came into the world, to alter, yea, and ouerthrow ſtates and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in al things wherin they ſhould be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto his wil, and I hope that you of this parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wil not deny him this prerogatiue. If I haue ſought the remouing of any thing, which the lord requireth not to be altered, I craue no pardon of mine ouerſight. What I haue written in this whol treatiſe, I am ready by the grace of God, perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make good (though it were vppon mine vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt peril) whenſoeuer I ſhalbe therevnto cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, by you of this honorable aſſembly; wherein there are many of good eſtimation and credit, who vpon the motion of mine apperance by this houſe, wil I truſt, vndertake that I ſhall come to ſtand vnto the premiſes by me ſet downe. So that I may obtain (which I moſt humbly craue of you, R. Hh. and worſhipful) that vpon mine apperance I be not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y any court, or prerogatiue (only the H. court of parliament excepted, vnto whom, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the higheſt councel in the land, in this cauſe I apeale) debarred of my liberty, before my cauſe according vnto the word be ouerthrowne. The injury which I ſuſtained the laſt parliament (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſuitor in this cauſe) enforceth me to craue this at your hands, which otherwiſe, I ſhould haue perſwaded my ſelfe to be a needles ſuit. For wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <pb n="79" facs="tcp:14778:47"/> the auncient priueledges and liberties of this houſe, do giue leaue (during the parliament) vnto any that are ſuitors thereunto, quietly to follow their ſuits without feare of any arreſt, and being arreſted, do preſently deliuer and ſet them free, I was not ſuffred to enioy any the former liberties. But contrary vnto all religion, law, equity, and conſcience, to the great derogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the liberties of this noble court, was committed cloſe priſoner by ſome, who abuſed the high commiſſion; their dealing might haue appeared more tollerable, &amp; leſſe derogatorious vnto your Hh. &amp; worſhips, if they had ſhewed any cauſe of mine impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (their abuſed authority only excepted) which vnto this day is altogether vnknowne vnto me.</p>
            <p>I know, that the infirmities and wants of men, who deale in good cauſes, are commonly beaten vppon the back of the cauſe they handle. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord knoweth how careful I haue bin to keepe it vnſpotted, and my ſelfe out of all vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary danger. Setting downe nothing before I had conſidered what might inſue, ether in regard of the matter or manner of deliuery. But why did I publiſh a matter of ſuch waight, before I aquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the parliament therewith? Whie it is publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ende, that the parliament may bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the ſuite, which could not be done by priuate writing. And it is but an vngodly ſhifte of thoſe that woulde ſmother the trueth, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it to be againſt the law, to moue the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in any ſuit that is printed. As thogh the ſuits of men vnto that high courte, were parliament ſtatutes. In deede if the parliament had enacted the remoouing out of Wales, all L. Bb. dumb mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14778:48"/> &amp;c. Then were it an intollerable part, for any to publiſhe their actes, but by their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Graunt you the petition, and the cauill of committing it to the preſſe, will eaſily be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. If you do not meane to yeeld vnto the ſuite, neither woulde you haue done it, being mooued therevnto by priuate writing. The cauſe I make knowne, to the end it may be granted, and herein let not my life be precious vnto me; vpon the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of the publiſhing hereof I ſtande, becauſe that the worlde may ſee when you redreſſe theſe things, that you did nothing, that you durſt leaue vndone, vnles you would bring ſwift deſtruction vpon your ſelues and the whole lande. But what follie is it to thinke, that ſuch great matters wilbe reformed in our dayes. Rather what injurie doe they vnto the whole ſtate, who thinke that they wil any longer tollerate the breach of Gods law. And in this point, let the good opinion, that they who alledge ſuch pretences conceiue, be wayed with my dutiful perſwaſions of this honorable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and both cauſes judged accordingly. For mine owne part, I think the majeſtie of the cauſe to be ſuch, as they who are the Lordes, dare not but entertaine it, and tremble to thinke, that all this while, it hath beene ſo careleſly attended vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And it is in the behalfe thereof, that I haue preſumed to deale with you, who otherwiſe durſt not haue ſuffered my voyce to be hearde, in the ears of the princes of my people. Let what I haue written bee examined, yea by mine aduerſaries themſelues (if I haue any) and it ſhal appeare, that I haue made a conſcience, howe I haue delt with my ſuperiors, eſpecially thoſe, concerning whom <pb n="81" facs="tcp:14778:48"/> it is ſaid, you are Gods, leſt I ſhould ſeem to leaue behinde me, the leaſt print of a minde in any ſort tending to defame them or their gouernement, As I haue bene carefull hereof, ſo let the Lorde, yea and no otherwiſe, (which I ſpeak as far as my corruptions will permit) grant this cauſe, and my ſelfe alſo, if it be his will, fauour in your eyes. In deed in regarde of the cauſe, I come Mandatorie wiſe, vnto this honorable aſſembly, but in regard of my ſelfe, I come in feare and trembling as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lords vicegerents, entreating moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that the dignitie of ſo high a cauſe, be thoght off, nothing the more diſhonorably, becauſe it is brought in my hands. And I proteſt in reſpect of my ſinnes, that the Lorde may juſtly denie it the fauour it deſerueth in your eyes, becauſe I am a dealer therein, But this ſhould be no reaſon why the parliament ſhould giue it a repulſe. For in the eyes and eares of al the world I make it knowne, that it is the cauſe of the liuing god wherin I deal And that if it had beene poſſible for me to haue written more humblye and dutifully, I had done it. Or if I had ſeene anye waye, that might haue bene likelier to preuaile wirh my ſuperiors, then this, I take the Lorde to witneſſe vnto my ſoule, that I woulde not haue vſed this courſe. And I would to God I could tel how to make the cauſe plawſible. So farre I am, from ſetting downe any thing, that might cary with it any ſhewe of occaſion to hinder and diſgrace the ſame. Well I haue don my endeuour, the ſucceſſe I expect at the Lords hands, vnto whome I commend the cauſe and the ſaluation of that poore people.</p>
            <p>The ſword of iuſtice reached vnto you by the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14778:49"/> Lord himſelfe, to take puniſhment onely of him that is an euil doer. I fear not, becauſe I haue not offended. If it ſhould be drawne againſt me for this action, the preſident would be ſuch, as they who ment herafter to propheſie vnto you, might be aduiſedly counſeled not to propheſie, and the Lord as a token of your iuſt deſtruction to enſue, would ſay they ſhal not propheſie nor take ſhame If I haue ſpoken any vntruth, beare witnes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if a trueth, I dare ſtand to it by the Lords aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and demand what he is that will preſume to obiect and throw him ſelfe vnto the vengance of God, by punniſhing me an innocente; It is a common manner with ſome in theſe dayes, to threaten thoſe who deale in this cauſe nowe in hand: but they are to know that it is not ſo eaſie a matter to ſpil their bloud, whoſe daies are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered with the Lord. The Lord may (I confeſſe with griefe) in regard of my other ſinnes, bringe mine head to the graue with bloud, but in this caſe what haue I offended? And therfore vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted woe wil betide him, that ſhall moleſt me for this worke. Howe ſoeuer it be, thus I haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed a duty towards the Lord, his church, my country, &amp; you of this high court, which I wold doe if it were to be done againe, though I were aſſured to endanger my life thereby. And be it knowne, that in this caſe I am not afraid of earth. If I periſh I periſh. My comforte is, that I knowe whither to go, &amp; in that day wherein the ſecrets of all hearts ſhal be manifeſted, the ſincerity alſo of my cauſe ſhal apeare. It is inough for me, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I be miſerable in regard of my ſinnes, that yet vnto Chriſt, I both liue and die, and purpoſe <pb n="83" facs="tcp:14778:49"/> by his grace, if my life ſhould be prolonged, to liue hereafter, not vnto my ſelfe, but vnto him and his church, otherwiſe then hitherto I haue don. The Lord is able to raiſe vp thoſe that are of puerer hands and lipps then I am, to write and ſpeak in the cauſe of his honor in Wales. And the Lord make them whoſoeuer they ſhalbe, neuer to be wanting vnto ſo good a cauſe; the which, becauſe it may be the Lords pleaſure, that I ſhal leaue them behind me in the world, I earneſtly and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently commend vnto them, as by this my laſt wil &amp; teſtament. And haue you R. honourable &amp; worſhipful of this parlirment, poore Wales in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, that the bleſſing of many a ſaued ſoule therein, may follow her Maieſtie, your Hh. and worſhips, overtake you, light vppon you, and ſtick vnto you for euer. The eternal God giue hir Maieſty &amp; you, the honor of building his church in Wales, multiply the daies of hir peace ouer vs, bleſſe her and you ſo in this life, that in the life to come, the inheritance of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, may be her and your portion. So be it good Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By him that hath bound him ſelfe continually to pray for your Hh. and worſhips. IOHN PENRI<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
